<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://dyang5.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://dyang5.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2023-08-27T21:35:48+00:00</updated><id>https://dyang5.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">David Yang</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Young Mathematicians Conference</title><link href="https://dyang5.github.io/blog/2023/YMC-writeup/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Young Mathematicians Conference"/><published>2023-08-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-08-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://dyang5.github.io/blog/2023/YMC-writeup</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://dyang5.github.io/blog/2023/YMC-writeup/"><![CDATA[<p><i>Hosted at The Ohio State University, August 15th - 17th.</i></p> <h4 id="day-0-august-14th"><u>Day 0: August 14th</u></h4> <p><b> Logistics </b></p> <p>I left for the airport at 6:30 AM. Since my girlfriend Sherry also had a work trip starting today (with a 8:15 flight time), I wanted to make sure I could leave with her and see that she would arrive safely – thus, the early wake up and travel time. After seeing Sherry go through the security checkpoint (for Southwest) relatively smoothly, I went over to concourse D to check into my flight, before then going through security as well (TSA Precheck made this process very easy). I had about three, four hours to kill, and I mainly texted friends, grabbed breakfast and later lunch from McDonalds, and listened to music. I took my first flight from BWI to DTW (Detroit), where I had another hour layover. This time, the flight from Detroit to Columbus, Ohio was overbooked, and so Delta ended up having to offer $1000 in gift cards to 7 passengers in exchange for them flying out on a later flight (my flight back from NCUR was similarly overbooked and a similar offer for $800 was made – I think if I had been returning home rather than arriving at the conference, I would have taken this deal, especially since the flight from DTW to CMH is only an hour long). Soon enough, though, I was on the plane to Columbus and I arrived at around 5.</p> <p>After grabbing my luggage from baggage claim, I ordered an Uber to the Blackwell Hotel, a super nice 4 star hotel that the conference is providing for us. I unpacked a few things, charged my devices, and sent a message on the Discord to ask if anyone wanted to grab dinner. I also prepped my presentation some more, even going through a rough practice run with a friend from my UMD REU. Luckily, I got one taker and so I officially met my first conference participant (YJ, though I did meet someone else in the elevator) and we went to dinner at Diaspora, a Korean-Japanese fusion restaurant.</p> <p>After dinner, I walked back to the hotel (YJ went off to the math building), where I made some calls to parents and friends before relaxing for the night. The OSU campus is quite nice – the hotel is also right next to a bunch of sports facilities including the football stadium – so it should be fun to be both a conference attendee and an explorer in the next few days.</p> <h4 id="day-1-august-15th"><u>Day 1: August 15th</u></h4> <p>In the morning, I woke up at 8 AM and chilled in bed until 9. After getting ready for the day and practicing a bit more on my presentation, I went to the hotel lobby to meet JLD, one of my high school friends who is also attending YMC (as a second-time participant – he came last year) for brunch. We ended up going to a nice brunch diner spot called Hangover Easy, where I got an Omelette and a Milkshake. It was great to catch up with him and to hear about his crazy travels/run schedule this summer (he got off the redeye, napped for two hours, then went for 6 miles at 7:00 pace before meeting me for brunch).</p> <p>After brunch, we walked over to the Math Building to first check in and then went up to the seventh floor to hang out with the other conference participants (this is where I will need to look up people’s last names – though everyone has a name tag, people usually introduce themselves with their first names and so that’s all I really remember). JLD ran into a few of his friends from Williams (he goes there and also did the SMALL REU there last summer) and went to talk with them, so I walked around the room and tried to meet other people. I first talked to CN, who participated in the Michigan Math REU, before briefly meeting CY and WZ, who participated in SUAMI. After making it back to my original table, I met a big Williams contingent, including both Williams students and SMALL participants (Williams/SMALL: FN, SC, KS, SD; also ZM from Swarthmore and a few others including CK and RT) and we chatted a bit until we had a big introductory announcement essentially welcoming us to the Conference and reminding us to fill out reimbursement details (I need to do that soon). We then socialized a bit more before heading down to Scott Hall to attend the first few student lectures.</p> <p>I attended the following (I took some notes and will try to LaTeX them up after the conference):</p> <ul> <li>(1:45 - 2:05 PM): <em>The Failed Zero Forcing Number of a Graph</em></li> <li>(2:15 - 2:35 PM): <em>Properties of Families of Graphs with Forbidden Induced Subgraphs</em></li> <li>(2:45 - 3:05 PM): <em>Random Discrete Decomposition and Benford’s Law</em></li> </ul> <p>[Mini Break for Snacks (M&amp;M Cookies, yum!) and Coffee, which tasted terrible but was much needed]</p> <ul> <li>(3:45 - 4:05 PM): <em>Exploring the Berezin Range of Operators on Subspaces of the Hardy Space</em></li> <li>(4:15 - 4:45 PM): <em>The VC Dimension of the Heisenberg Group</em></li> </ul> <p>At 5:00, we had our first plenary lecture on <em>The Collatz Conjecture over the Gaussian Integers</em> by Professor Alejandra Alvarado (Eastern Illinois University). After that, we all went back to the Math Tower to enjoy some Mediterranean Catering for dinner and socialized a bit more with the other participants. At this point, my social battery as well as the others seemed to be dissipating. I met a few other participants throughout the day and here (JN, LOB, JJ, and JL – the latter two of which know Philip, one of my research partners from the Circle Packings presentation I’m presenting here, from various places, which was insane… I guess it really is a small world out there). Afterwards, I went back to the hotel with JN, CY, and TC, where I practiced my presentation some more and decompressed for the day. It was definitely a hectic day today – more presentations tomorrow and hopefully more free time (I really want to explore the campus, including the football stadium and the beautiful surrounding area).</p> <h4 id="day-2-august-16th"><u>Day 2: August 16th</u></h4> <p>The organizers mentioned yesterday that conference breakfast would be provided for at 8:30 AM at the Math Tower. Since I’m not really a breakfast person, and though I did end up waking up around 8, I took a bit longer than normal to get ready, and left the hotel at 9. In the lobby, I ran into AZ and JN, and we walked over to the Math Tower to find that all the breakfast pastries were gone (they brought it in 30 minutes prior, so it’s really just our fault). I grabbed two cups of orange juice and chatted with JLD and a few others before walking to the second plenary lecture in the EA building.</p> <p>The plenary talk today was <em>Practical Applications of Complex Analysis</em> by Professor Loredana Lanzani of Syracuse University and University of Bologna. I really enjoyed the plenary lecture. As the title suggests, the talk mainly highlighted the power of conformal maps in cultural/historical contexts (such as in airplane wing design, art like the Droste effect, as well as quasi-conformal mappings and their use in morphometric analysis). The talk reminded me of the Swarthmore IMC (Interactive Math Colloquium) I hosted where Professor Janet Talvacchia talked about the history of Geometry and Spaces and related concepts – and I very much enjoyed it.</p> <p>After the plenary lectures, we went down to Scott Hall to watch the student lectures. Today, a lot of my friends from school (like ZM, who I know from Swarthmore and JLD, who I know from high school) and the conference were presenting, but unfortunately there were a lot of time conflicts between presentations. I attended the following presentations (and offered to take pictures for most of the presenters as well)</p> <ul> <li>(11 - 11:20): <em>A Structure Theorem on Doubling Measures for Arbitrary Bases</em> (ZM’s talk)</li> <li>(11:30 - 11:50): <em>Binomial Sets Under Z-Linear Forms</em></li> </ul> <p>We had a brief poster session, where we heard two posters from conference attendees (one of the presenters JJ also knows my friend Philip, my research collaborator from Swarthmore who could not be at YMC, from their REU – it’s cool how connected everyone is), before getting the provided catering lunch. It turns out that there was a different conference going on at the other side of the hall, with their own provided catering lunch from QDoba… the food smelled so good and I ended up attempting to grab some food with JLD, to no avail. We unfortunately had to wait longer to grab our conference’s food, which was okay, as well as the YMC t-shirts for this year.</p> <p>Since I finished my food pretty quickly and there was an extra hour to spare before the next round of student presentations, I decided to walk around and explore campus. I first hit the nearest Starbucks to get some coffee before heading over to the Student Union to grab a picture with Brutus the Buckeye. I then walked back to the Math Tower/Scott Hall to hear the next round of talks:</p> <ul> <li>(1:45 - 2:05 PM): <em>Generalizations of the Erdos–Ginzburg–Ziv theorem via topology</em> (JLD’s talk)</li> <li>(2:15 - 2:35 PM): <em>On the Size and Complexity of Scrambles</em> (a SMALL REU talk by KS and SD, two friends I met from the conference)</li> <li>(2:45 - 3:05 PM): <em>Finite Rank Sequences Over Arbitrary Finite Alphabets</em></li> </ul> <p>At this point, I was feeling quite tired so I went to the Math Lounge to decompress before the next event, a grad school panel where a few professors answered grad school and application questions. Steven Miller, the SMALL REU head, was also a part of the panel and he had some great news – he would be providing everyone with pizza for dinner. I was happy at first about this but also a bit sad since I wanted to explore Columbus and the dinner spots with a few other conference participants… after dinner, I played a game of chess with CP before deciding to return to the hotel and throw around a frisbee with KS, CP, and later TO and CY. At around 6:30, I returned back to the hotel to decompress, practice and finalize my presentation a few times, and called my parents and friends to close out the night.</p> <p>It’s crazy how fast this conference has gone – tomorrow is presentation day for me but also the last official day of the conference (I’m flying out of Columbus at 5). I wish we had more time here to explore but my main priority tomorrow will be to close out the conference experience strong with a solid presentation.</p> <h4 id="day-3-august-17th"><u>Day 3: August 17th</u></h4> <p>Last day of the conference today! I woke up to my alarm at around 7:30 today – my (optimistic) plan that I made last night was to wake up early, grab some breakfast from Panera Bread, and then head back to the hotel to shower, practice my presentation, pack my bags, and check out of the hotel. After waking up kind of tired, though, these plans changed immediately. I decided to not rush anything and skip breakfast to pack, shower, and practice my presentation again. One of my research partners Philip (who is currently in Budapest) sent me some suggestions for the presentation (I sent him a recorded video of a practice runthrough and he gave me feedback on that), and so I tried to incorporate his feedback in my morning practice talk. After doing my run through, I finished up my suitcase packing, tidied up the hotel room, and went down to the lobby to check out for the day. Despite having already checked out, the hotel let me I was able to store my suitcase there to pick up after the conference, which was quite convenient.</p> <p>After checking out, I went over to the Math Tower to grab a small breakfast (a cup of OJ and a M&amp;M Cookie in this instance) to calm down my presentation nerves. As a large conference group, we then went over to the EA building to listen to our final plenary lecture of the conference, <em>Topology meets Physics: Scissors Congruences and TQFTs</em> by Professor Carmen Rovi of Loyola University. The talk itself was quite good – I followed for most of the first half before getting a bit more lost (and tired/nervous for my own presentation) at the cut-and-paste-operations and TQFT part. I especially enjoyed the scissor congruence animations she had – I thought they showcased the concept quite well. The end of the presentation could not have been more timely – right around 10:30, the fire alarms started going off since OSU was doing tests on their alarm system. As a conference group, we went outside to snap a few group conference photos (most of us were wearing the YMC 2023 shirts for the occasion). I grabbed a few other photos with a smaller group of students who all know Philip before heading inside to the Scott Hall to prep for my presentation.</p> <p>Since my presentation was at 11, I scouted out the area nearly 20 minutes before, only to find that none of the classrooms had anyone in them. With around 10 minutes until presentation time, I got a bit more nervous, since there still seemed to not be anyone around. Luckily, the moderator for my session showed up shortly afterwards, and with some help, I was able to get connected to the big computer and get my presentation up on the projector. At this point, the nerves started to settle in. Quite a few people trickled in with a few minutes to go, and I was mainly waiting anxiously, doing my signature nervous cough, and chugging water. I soon got introduced as the first presentation speaker, gave my presentation relatively smoothly, and answered a few questions – it was a solid presentation experience (any pictures taken are courtesy of ZM and JLD). The presentations I went to today included:</p> <ul> <li>(11 - 11:20 AM): <em>Circle Packings from Tilings of the Plane</em> (my own)! <blockquote> <p>The presentation itself went pretty well. I’d say I fibbed/stumbled a bit for only a few small parts, but that’s always kind of to be expected due to nerves, even though I’ve done a lot of practice on this talk. I got a number of solid questions at the end as well, including quite a few “nice job!” and “nice presentation!” comments from the other participants, which is always nice to have. In terms of the content itself, a lot of people were happy about the presentation visuals and were curious as to how we drew them (Tikz for most of them – the circles are mostly handcoded – with the exception of the final few slides which were done with a Python program). Overall, I was quite happy with how the presentation went and was proud of how I did!</p> </blockquote> </li> <li>(11:30 - 11:50 AM): <em>Dehn Invariant Zero Tetrahedra</em> <blockquote> <p>This talk was related to the Scissors Congruence talk we had earlier for the plenary lecture which was cool to see!</p> </blockquote> </li> <li>(12 - 12:20 PM): <em>Distance Graph Embedding Problems over Finite Fields</em></li> </ul> <p>After this final round of talks, we all went over to one of the presentation rooms for the YMC’s closing remarks. We got a brief speech about why OSU and some of the benefits of the Math Grad program there (as well as a few goodies including pins, pens, and stickers) before the organizers of YMC thanked us and everyone involved for the conference experience. Since people were rushing to catch their flights (JLD already left to the airport – he actually scootered the 8 miles there), this farewell message was short. We all gathered outside once again, and I got a quick picture with KS before he left with some of the other SMALL participants. ZM, JC, JL, and I decided to head somewhere for lunch to conclude the experience, and we were later joined by YJ and AS along the way. We ended up going to a nice little cafe, had a nice chat (at some point YJ and JC had to leave, but we were later joined by JJ and a few other friends), and grabbed some pictures before I decided that I had to head back to make my flight. After walking back to the hotel, grabbing my suitcase, calling an Uber to the airport, that was effectively the end of my conference experience!</p> <h4 id="-acknowledgements"><b> Acknowledgements</b></h4> <p>In general, I’m really glad I got the chance to participate in YMC this year and grateful that I was accepted. I would have enjoyed more time to explore the campus (I really wanted to but did not get to go to the Ohio Football Stadium) and meet more people, but the program was packed with activities and events already. It was great to meet everyone and I can’t wait for the next conference I get to go to!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="swarthmore"/><category term="research"/><category term="math"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[my conference experience at the 2023 Young Mathematicians Conference (YMC).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">REU-CAAR, Week 10</title><link href="https://dyang5.github.io/blog/2023/REUCAAR-week10/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="REU-CAAR, Week 10"/><published>2023-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://dyang5.github.io/blog/2023/REUCAAR-week10</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://dyang5.github.io/blog/2023/REUCAAR-week10/"><![CDATA[<h4 id="day-64-august-7th-"><u>Day 64 (August 7th) </u></h4> <p>Week 10 Day 1: The Final Week</p> <ul> <li> <p>8:30 - 9:00 AM: As is tradition at the start of each week: Week 10 here we go! It’s crazy to think it really is going to be the end of the REU in just a few days. I’m definitely going to try to make the most of the time we have together and also hopefully finish strong research-wise as well. To kick off this final week, I decided to go for a classic 2 mile morning run. Legs definitely felt quite tired with all the running/sprinting I did yesterday, but it was good to get a nice workout in. Since my group and I asked LH to be our “friend” (Bill wants all practice presentations to have a “friend” who has not seen our presentation to act as an unbiased, secondary feedback-giver along with Clyde Kruskal), she also asked me this morning to sit into her presentation. This meant that I had to shower quickly and head out earlier than normal to make sure I made it by 9:45.</p> </li> <li> <p>9:45 AM - 12:00 PM: I made it over to the CSI building at 9:45, running in to LH along the way. There, I listened to LH, GP, and AZ’s project presentation (Machine Translation for Wikipedia), which was quite good. Though this was their group’s second round of feedback, Clyde gave pretty solid feedback on each of their slides – so much so that he went 25 minutes over, leading to a slight delay for each of the next few groups. The MT group’s talk went until around 11 AM, after which I promptly headed over to talk with my group about our project. I finished up one of the slides I was working on last night, and worked slightly past our typical lunch time. I totally forgot that Bill was hosting a lunch talk but that didn’t seem to be a problem…</p> </li> <li> <p>12:00 - 1:30 PM: Bill was scheduled to give his lunch talk “Trick Questions or Stupid Questions” starting at 12, but since the presentation groups got a bit delayed, we didn’t start until 12:30. The talk itself was solid, as all Bill talks have been, and mainly consisted of him asking us math-ish riddles, giving us the answer, and then asking if the question was a trick or just stupid.</p> </li> <li> <p>1:30 - 3:00 PM: After the talk, I went up to our conference room to get in some more work and finish up the presentation. Our big order of business this week is to deliver our final presentation Wednesday morning, so I’ve been doing what I can to make the presentation orderly and understandable. In the afternoon, this mainly consisted of adding animations to relevant slides, reorganizing details, and then doing a practice runthrough right before we were scheduled to present. The practice runthrough itself went to about 22 minutes, which is not great considering our presentation is supposed to be between 15 and 20. This was the first time we practiced as an entire group – it has been kind of hard to get everyone together and actually go through with the presentation (and I get the sense the others care a bit less about it than I do); in the middle of our practice presentation, we also received an email from Bill that due to the schoolwide tornado warning, we were to head “home” and that our presentation (which was meant for the 3 - 4 PM time slot) would be rescheduled. This was definitely a blow to my group – all other groups have already done two rounds of presentations with Clyde whereas we haven’t even gotten a single one (due to AF being out last week and the tornado warning today). While I understand that Bill probably picked the 3-4 PM time slot for us since if we went over, we wouldn’t delay the other groups’ presentations, and that today’s tornado warning couldn’t have been forecasted, it just sucks that we haven’t gotten any outside feedback yet/done any official runthroughs. (We are now scheduled for a Zoom one tomorrow at 11 AM, the day before our presentation, which is better than nothing at this point).</p> </li> </ul> <p>Per the tornado warning, most of the REU group congregated in my suite. We ended up talking for a bit and playing some Jackbox (online group game). For dinner, since the Student Union was closed, I made some Ramen and Soba (courtesy of a big package order from my parents) and then rejoined the group to watch some Kung Fu Panda. The night activity they were planning involved alcohol at the very least so I decided to hold off on that, and retire to my room to organize the presentation and work on some CodeForces. Looking forward to tomorrow – hopefully we get some solid (I imagine it will be quite useful for us as well) advice on our presentation and that we clutch up for the big one on Wednesday! There are also rumblings of a plan to go to the beach post-research and that will be nice if it ends up happening…</p> <h4 id="day-65-august-8th-"><u>Day 65 (August 8th) </u></h4> <p>Week 10 Day 2: Prep Day</p> <ul> <li> <p>8:30 AM - 9:00 AM: I ended up sleeping a bit later than I’d have liked yesterday – I ended up joining some of the other REU students upstairs and talking before working a bit on the presentation and calling it a night. As such, I decided to get some extra sleep in today in the morning.</p> </li> <li> <p>10:00 AM - 12:30 PM: In the morning, I did some final runthroughs of the presentation – fixing up some of my parts – before joining up with AF, SS, and XG for our practice presentation with Clyde Kruskal. The meeting itself went fine – we got a lot of useful feedback on our beginning slides, and Clyde seemed to be fine with a number of our later slides (I thought that was kind of surprising considering the feedback he gave to other groups, but I suppose this is a good thing). The meeting ended up going over time and we got kicked out by a different group who had reserved the conference room for 12:30.</p> </li> <li> <p>1:30 - 4:00 PM: After lunch, a large group of us went to the Campus Bookstore to spend our remaining meal money on campus merchandise. PM spent around $650 on clothes (including some for others in the REU – a large portion of us purchased the same “Smiley” Maryland shirt and we all plan to wear it tomorrow to the presentation), and I got myself the smiley shirt. Instead of heading back to IRB afterwards, I helped PM move his new purchases to his room, and afterwards, I fixed up some of the slides per Clyde’s suggestions. Our group convened in the basement for a final practice presentation to round out the day.</p> </li> </ul> <p>Post-research, XG, LH, SS, AF, and I drove to the beach, where we met up with ZS, SK, DS, and MA. I mainly threw around the football with DS (even joining a game with some other non-REU beach people) while the remainder of the group played near the water (there were a bunch of baby jellyfish so we didn’t do anything crazy in there) and played around with the sand. We got quite a few pictures to commemorate the occasion – MA is leaving tomorrow after the presentation so we made sure to enjoy our “final moments of the REU” with him. Afterwards, we ended up going for dinner at a local burger place and arrived back at home at 10:45 PM… I brushed up, showered, did some CodeForces, and made some final touches to the presentation, while getting in a bit more practice. It’s crazy to think the culmination of our 10 weeks of work will be all presented tomorrow – fingers crossed everything goes fine! Let’s finish strong. :)</p> <h4 id="day-66-august-9th-"><u>Day 66 (August 9th) </u></h4> <p>Week 10 Day 3: Final Presentations and Round 1 of Goodbyes</p> <ul> <li> <p>8:30 - 9:00 AM: Today was the day of our final presentations! Since the presentations were due to start at 9:30, I wanted to wake up, shower, and then run through the presentation a bit more before heading over to IRB.</p> </li> <li> <p>9:30 AM - 12:30 PM: The presentations started at 9:30, with the presentation order as: Parallel Algorithms, Fair Decision Making (us), Machine Translation, Computational Geometry, Markov Chains for Climate Change, then Quantum Computations. Though we were scheduled to present second, XG somehow misset his alarm and thus we ended up geting moved two slots back. Besides this being a minor incovenience (and us momentarily figuring out how/whether we should cover for his slides), it didn’t mean much in the long run, and our presentation went relatively smoothly. We got a number of questions afterwards about our approaches/general comments from Bill, which is good since it seems like people were following along well. I was a bit bummed that our advisor, who had asked when the final presentations were, didn’t end up making it to watch (she initially said she was running late, then asked about remote participation when we told her the presentation got delayed, but there was no such option) but that’s okay – the presentation is more for us to conclude and summarize our work in the program. The rest of the talks were quite good; I ended up taking a few pictures for my friends during their presentations to send to them afterwards. After the presentations, we convened outside to take some group pictures, including quite a few of them with just people with the Smiley Maryland hoodie (my group, the Comp Geo group, the Parallel group, and a few others agreed to wear it during the presentation) and a few individual pictures with Bill.</p> </li> <li> <p>1:00 - 4:00 PM: In place of research after lunch, we mainly hung around with MA and PM, since they were scheduled to leave today. The goodbyes were difficult, especially since MA and PM were instrumental in making the REU more fun for everyone. MA left around 2:30, and we again took a bunch of pictures before bidding him goodbye. PM left a bit later – we hung around in his apartment, helped him move all of his stuff to the car (there was a lot, including at least six pairs of shoes, a TV, and more…), before taking some time to say goodbyes once more. There will definitely be more farewells in the coming days but I hope we all keep in contact and go on to do great things!</p> </li> </ul> <p>Post research, we mainly sat around and talked with each other before heading to CFA for dinner. We worked on a math riddle AF gave us (say you have an island with knights and spades – knights who always tell the truth and spades who can lie. Given there are n spades and knights, and there are more knights than spades, construct a O(n) algorithm to find a knight) for a while afterwards before retracing our steps in the morning to find DS’s lost longboard. I did a quick one mile run in khakis and a polo on the way back, before showering and relaxing for the night.</p> <p>There are just a few more official days left of the REU – it’s certainly been a memorable experience that I’ve been really glad to have. Tomorrow, we are watching the Computational Biology REU’s talks (they watched ours today), which should be fun.</p> <h4 id="day-67-august-10th-"><u>Day 67 (August 10th) </u></h4> <p>Week 10 Day 4: REU-BRIDGE Participants</p> <ul> <li> <p>9:30 AM - 12:30 PM: The REU-BRIDGE presentations (for biology) started at 9:30 – I got there a few minutes late and ended up taking a back seat near Bill. We watched 5 of the presentations, took a quick break (I snagged some coffee – which tasted terrible – and some Dunkin Donuts from the snack station along the way), before listening to the last 5. There was one presentation that I thought was hilarious – it was called SmartUnderwear, which is just a device for measuring flatulence (essentially farts). Most of the talks were pretty solid; I understood them to a varying degree, with me understanding more of the first few presentations in each block of 5.</p> </li> <li> <p>1:00 - 4:00 PM: After lunch, we walked around in the bookstore again to spend our remaining meal money (I got a Maryland sweater for Sherry, outerwear for me, and a Hydroflask to replace my broken water bottle – leaving me with just 10 bucks). I then went back to do some laundry and relax, before hanging out with the other REU kids.</p> </li> </ul> <p>We played some group games like charades (which I thought was quite fun), talked a bit more as a group, and decided to head to Wawa for dinner. CL, MT (both of which are high school students), DS, and I took one car while ZS, XG, AF, and LH took the other. We returned back to the dorms to eat our food (I thought the Wawa food wasn’t too good but that may just be because I haven’t really had an apetitite lately) before hanging out and talking for the night. Tomorrow is our official “Farewell Talk” and “Farewell Dinner”, and a lot of students will be leaving tomorrow, so I’ll be sure to wish everyone a goodbye before I head out on Saturday.</p> <h4 id="day-68-august-11th"><u>Day 68 (August 11th)</u></h4> <p>Week 10 Day 5: Farewell Presentation and Discussion(s)</p> <ul> <li> <p>9:00 - 10:00 AM: Today was the official last day of the REU. I ended up staying up quite late talking to SS, LH, XG, DS, and AF yesterday night – especially since it was SS’s last full day at the REU (the remainder of us were planning on leaving Saturday or later). To commemorate a fun ten weeks, we planned to head over to Vigilante Coffee to grab some coffee and acai bowls (as we did on the first day). However, our plans changed (mostly due to lack of sleep by SS) and instead we decided to head to the Starbucks in STAMP. We grabbed some farewell pictures with SS and then walked over to IRB. On the way there, we ran into SK who said her goodbyes to SS. At a random intersection, SS decided to head back (she had walked with us to accompany us but was scheduled to leave without hearing the farewell talk) and so we did some group hugs and said goodbye.</p> </li> <li> <p>10:00 AM - 12:00 PM: To cap off the REU, Bill gave a “farewell talk,” which was similar in style to the intro talk that we had on the first day. It was nice to reflect on the program’s successes, and he also responded to feedback that we had sent him previously on how to improve the program. We each went around and talked about our favorite parts of the program and then afterwards got some Olive Garden catering. While a bunch of students (including CK, JS, NL, AZ, ZS, AB, ML, and maybe more) left to get packing, a few of us stayed behind to talk more with Bill and asked him some questions. We also worked on a few math puzzles that he gave us (one problem was to show that you cannot 3-color the positive integers less than 2000 such that numbers that differ by a perfect square have different colors. Note: we found a much smaller bound than 2000 in 59, and the smallest such bound is apparently 29). It was a nice way to wrap up this farewell gathering by working on some group problems with CL, DS, AF, SK, and to some extent, MT and LH.</p> </li> </ul> <p>Afterwards, we all headed back to the dorms to relax while people who were leaving packed some more. We bid our farewells to CK and AZ at 2ish, and later, ML and AB at 3ish. I made sure to get as many photos together as I could to commemorate the occasion – after all, it’s been a nice 10 weeks with everyone. We went back to our suite before throwing around a football (mainly me, DS, and XG) with CL, as LH, SK, and AF relaxed in the grass. We snapped some group pictures once again before saying goodbye to CL and walking him to his car. The remainder of us stopped at the nearby rolled ice cream spot afterwards to grab some ice cream and chill while playing Contact. Afterwards, we retired to our rooms to pack up some more and made some dinner plans, as we wanted to enjoy our last dinner together. Since AF’s parents were coming later and planned to have dinner with her, SK, LH, XG, DS, and I decided to head to dinner at the College Park Grill with DS’s mom, who was also around to travel back with him. It was nice to meet her, and we had a nice chat about some of the program’s best moments and our projects. After walking back to our suite, we decided to watch some funny YouTube videos together and play some group Charades once more before each retiring for the night. I ended up spending a bit more time packing up before getting some much needed sleep.</p> <h4 id="day-69-august-12th"><u>Day 69 (August 12th)</u></h4> <p>Week 10 Day 6: Final Farewells</p> <p>Today was the day of farewells, with SK, AF, DS, and I scheduled to leave today. After a night of more than 6 hours of sleep (I got 7 today), I woke up to my 8:15 alarm – SK was due to leave at 8:30, so I woke up DS and joined LH and AF to say goodbye to her. We got a few pictures (courtesy of Bill Gasarch) and watched as they drove away to drop SK at the airport.</p> <p>To enjoy each other’s company a bit more, we decided to head towards Dunkin’ Donuts as a group to get some coffee and some breakfast, as we reminisced on the program and how sad it was to say our goodbyes. When we got back to the dorms, we (XG also joined us around this time) ran into AF’s parents, and we exchanged some pleasantries before heading back up to individually pack our suitcases. AF left around 11, and we did the typical picture taking and group hugs. We had planned to get a nice photo with LH where I was to put my hands on their heads (since they always say I act like their “mother” or older sibling), and we forgot to do that, until LH and I decided to walk over to AF’s car as she was leaving and stop their parents to grab one last photo (I’m definitely happy we got it).</p> <p>After AF left, I helped DS to clean our suite before packing some more of my individual stuff. After a good 30 min - 1 hr, DS’s mom came by, and she helped lead the charge in cleaning up more and clearing out the fridge. After quite a few trips to the trash/recycle dumpsters and to the donation site in the basement, we helped DS move his stuff out the dorm and once again said our goodbyes. Out of the suite, I was definitely closest to DS and it was quite sad to see him go.</p> <p>Since most of my stuff was packed, I went up to the suite and packed my final things, before heading out for a walk to return my keys and to chat with LH, one of the students I was closest to in the REU. We had a nice chat to round out the REU – I told her I was especially grateful for the fact that she helped me reflect on my future goal/purpose in academia; I may not ever be (or even need to strive to be) the best or most accomplished researcher, but if I can help my students and more importantly the people around me in any way, whether that’s teaching them new concepts or just helping them be happy, then I will have made a lasting impact on them. (I feel like what I just wrote isn’t the best description of my thoughts so feel free to reach out if you want me to expand on these feelings). After the walk, LH and XG helped me move my belongings out of the dorm, I waited for an extremely expensive Uber (hopefully reimbursement covers this), and I bid my farewells to them and the REU as a whole.</p> <p>I am so grateful for the experience itself, and especially owe everything to my fellow REU participants, who made the program so much more rewarding and enjoyable. In no particular order, thank you to DS, SS, LH, AF, SK, XG, PM, MA, CL, AB, ML, ZS, AZ, NL, CK, JS, GP, MT, as well as Bill and Auguste for this incredible summer experience.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="caar"/><category term="research"/><category term="cs"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Week 10 of my Summer 2023 experience @ REU-CAAR.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">REU-CAAR, Week 9</title><link href="https://dyang5.github.io/blog/2023/REUCAAR-week9/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="REU-CAAR, Week 9"/><published>2023-08-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-08-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://dyang5.github.io/blog/2023/REUCAAR-week9</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://dyang5.github.io/blog/2023/REUCAAR-week9/"><![CDATA[<h4 id="day-57-july-31st-"><u>Day 57 (July 31st) </u></h4> <p>Week 9 Day 1: 1.5 to Go</p> <ul> <li> <p>8:30 - 9:00 AM: Week 9, here we go. Though there are technically two weeks left in the program, it’s really closer to 1.5 considering we have our final presentation next Wednesday. This means go time in terms of finalizing our research process/presentations (we have a practice presentation on August 7th and a final meeting sometime August 3rd with our advisor as well). With my stomach problems, I’ve been avoiding any heavy exercise – so no swimming or running for a while – but today I wanted to go out and get some exercise with an “easy run.” This ended up working out fine, since I got an extra thirty minutes of sleep that I would have used on the walking commute to and from the gym if I had gone to the pool instead. I made it back in time for a shower at my typical time before heading out for research in the morning.</p> </li> <li> <p>10:00 - 10:40 AM: Today’s research schedule was a bit weird. AF, XG, SS, and I congregated in our normal room, discussed general approaches (and XG gave me some valuable advice about how to fix the CUDA out of memory errors I’ve been getting – instead of requesting extra memory, request a “better” GPU), what we should have done before the next meeting with our advisor, and presentation plans. This was a productive discussion, but it was cut short because we were to head to REU talks by students from Salisbury in the nearby AV Williams Building.</p> </li> <li> <p>11:00 AM - 12:30 PM: The Salisbury REU program students gave talks on Homologies, Using Machine Learning to Study Tumors, ML for Oyster Classification, Parallel Matching (similar to Gale-Shapley), Social Network Study, and Deep Learning for Satellite Imagery. They were all pretty good, especially for work done over a short summer program. I thought it was pretty funny that the Oyster Project also used YOLOv8, an object detector that we used for face detection in our project.</p> </li> </ul> <p>After the talks, a full room of nearly 100 students, faculty, and parents were anxious for lunch… with the catering yet to arrive.</p> <ul> <li>12:30 - 2:30 PM: Instead of taking a break for lunch, we jumped into the next round of activities, which included Grad Program Information from UMD CS, AMSC (Applied Math, Scientific Computing), as well as a panel of Grad Students sharing their experiences. I learned some useful information for my application – including that CS seems to match students to advisors during the application process whereas AMSC is much more lax about selecting an advisor due to the breadth of options available. In this sense, I learned that for my CS applications, I will need to be much more tailored to the area I want to study, whereas for AMSC (which I am pretty interested in), I can speak more broadly about my background and why I might be a good fit.</li> </ul> <p>Somewhere along the line, the Panera lunch came in, with everyone running over to secure their food. I was already sitting closer to the back, so I managed to snag a box lunch without pushing or shoving, but I think the lunch process could have been a bit orderely – I’m not a big fan of the people who push and shove to get their top lunch choice, especially when there are so many people and, as I’d pointed out, likely not enough lunches. I felt particularly bad for the Salisbury students, who were sitting in the front due to their presentations; many of them did not end up getting a box lunch and instead went to IRB or Panda Express to get some food.</p> <ul> <li>2:30 - 4:00 PM: With the REU activities and grad panel, today was a much shorter research day than anticipated. When we came back from the talks, I got to work trying to test my code on a better GPU – I definitely got more images generated than normal, which was great. One of the main things we’ll need to consider is how to get better edit weights – currently, with the approach I’m using, a set of male dominated images will become female dominated after editing; however, I’m trying to get it much closer to a 50-50 split. I suppose that I could just select a few of the images to edit based on the overall distribution, but this doesn’t seem very elegant as a fix, though I guess that could be said about the SEGA approach as a whole.</li> </ul> <p>After research, I went straight to Today’s Hair to get a haircut – which was quite needed. Heading back to the dorms, I talked with DS a bit inside before deciding to head out on another run (2 mile one just like in the morning) to get some more exercise in on a nice day. I ended up coming back, only for ML and AB to be in the shower cue, so I promptly went out to the dining hall with LH for dinner. We ended up having a good conversation, which reminded me how nice it is to be talking with other REU students :) I came back and showered, and then we met up with AB, SS, DS, and XG to watch the movie “No Hard Feelings.” I got some CodeForces done along the way (with an extra hour of debugging needed after the movie) and unfortunately also ended up losing my keys (which is not good – I got a spare for now but will need to find them. I do think they’re somewhere in the suite though which should limit potential spots) before calling it a night. I think I’ll definitely need to work extra hard this week to get the presentation going and to prepare a good summary of the work we’ve done – tomorrow will be a big day on this front.</p> <h4 id="day-58-august-1st-"><u>Day 58 (August 1st) </u></h4> <p>Week 9 Day 2</p> <ul> <li> <p>8:30 - 9:00 AM: I woke up pretty tired and so I snoozed the alarm for another thirty minutes. After waking up at 8:30, my stomach didn’t feel too great so I decided to skip my morning workout. Excuses are excuses at this point, but if there’s any solace in the fact that I skipped, I did run twice yesterday, so technically my evening run yesterday can replace my intended morning run today. My keys did end up turning up, however, which was the highlight of my morning – it turns out DS took mine, mistaking it for his, and he ended up with two keys in his room last night. Minor complications aside, it’s good to have them back as the room replacement key prices are expensive (I would have to pay only if I had not found them).</p> </li> <li> <p>10:00 AM - 12:00 PM: My group found out that our advisor is actually back in the States and will be available for an in-person meeting on Thursday. Unfortunately, that timing coincides with a number of events, including AF heading out-of-state from Thursday to Saturday. We have planned a Thursday meeting from 4 - 5 with our advisor in which we’ll Zoom AF in. In terms of research, I talked a bit about my group about the presentation and our research approaches. After some discussion, I felt that my group wasn’t really too worried about the presentation – not sure to take this as a positive or a negative – but I really want to make sure we summarize and present our work well. I did end up agreeing, however, that the Beamer presentation that I ended up starting might not be the best idea given Beamer’s positioning troubles and the fact that we don’t have anything math-y we need to present, so I decided to switch to Google Slides. I do like the professionalism of Beamer templates so I think I’ll end up recreating the Beamer template in Slides, but Slides will definitely be easier to use. I worked a bit more on my Semantic Guidance approach, including setting up a general pipeline that varies the seeds (which is similar to the Fair Diffusion approach) during generation – we’ll use this when we generate lots of images.</p> </li> <li> <p>1:15 - 4:00 PM: In the afternoon session, I started a bit of the presentation (mainly setting up the Beamer presentation in Google Slides) and experimented more with SEGA. SS has been a bit discouraged about her erasing concepts approach so I pushed all my code to the GitHub and took some time to explain the approach/experimentation I’ve done thus far to her. I think with the code I have so far, we have “solved”/can solve batch gender fairness (more fair gender representation in a batch of images), but for some reason, when I include races as guidance categories, the image output changes drastically (the background no longer stays the same which is exactly what SEGA should be doing). I tried experimenting a bit with why this was the case, but SS is now working on seeing if we can solve group batch gender fairness. I think there is good progress being made here but I wish that I had not lost a few days of work to the stomachache – if we had another week or two I think we would have much more solid presentation results, but alas, that’s just the way the cookie crumbles sometimes.</p> </li> </ul> <p>After research, I joined DS, SS, and PM, who made plans to go to the gym. After some deciding/arguing about what activities we were going to do, we just decided to head out and not worry about it. When we got to the weight room, the badminton courts were also empty, so we decided to do weights and badminton. For some reason, PM was quite interested in how much I could bench (I have not done weight training in my life), and so after some convincing, I managed to work myself up to a failed bench of 125 pounds (XG and PM were giving me tips and spotting me) before successfully completing 125 and 135 pound benches, which I was very much surpised (and happy) about. After a failed attempt on 140, I decided to stop the weights there and went out to play badminton with DS – SS and PM joined shortly after. Badminton was also pretty fun – I was quite bad at first (and quite expressive on the court), but I got better after hitting around and it ended up being a good time. We went to the dining hall (I first met up with LH since I offered to pay for her – she has much less on her card than me) and DS, SS, XG, and PM joined us after.</p> <p>In the rest of the evening, I did some laundry (this was a bit annoying since both dryers and washers were full both times I went – I felt bad about taking out other people’s clothes but I luckily noticed that one of the piles was DS’s, so I called him to take out his laundry which freed up a slot for me), coding, and worked a bit on the presentation before calling it a night. These have certainly been an eventful last few days but I think it’s important to spend as much group time as I can with everyone before the REU ends.</p> <p>As a side note, my girlfriend Sherry is finally moving into her apartment for her full-time work starting soon, which is awesome! I’m very proud and hope that she settles in well (hi if you’re reading this!) – she is actually planning to visit sometime soon so that will be fun as well.</p> <h4 id="day-59-august-2nd-"><u>Day 59 (August 2nd) </u></h4> <p>Week 9 Day 3</p> <ul> <li> <p>8:30 - 9:00 AM: Got out for some morning exercise this morning with a 2 mile run. It’s good to get back into the groove of things exercise-wise, especially because I think it sets me up well for the work day.</p> </li> <li> <p>10:00 AM - 12:00 PM: In the morning, I mostly worked alone. My group didn’t end up arriving until later, but I focused on building on the presentation slides I worked on yesterday and testing the SEGA approach more. As I found previously, the SEGA is working pretty well (even compared to the Fair Diffusion approach) when I am using gender guidance, but not as well when I am attempting to guide both the race and the gender, since the image output seems to get completely changed. After a few failed attempts of tinkering with the weights more and seeing if that would change anything, I finally figured out why this is the case – in one of my lines of code, I was setting the pipeline of the generated image to a different random seed than the other generated images – this is the main cause in the complete change of the output of the image!</p> </li> <li> <p>12:00 - 2:00 PM: The UMD Math REU had their final poster presentations today, and REU-CAAR was invited to come listen. Overall, I thought the posters were quite well done. Considering their program is only 8 weeks long, I felt that their overall work was quite impressive. I listened to a majority of the poster presenters, including ones about Cluster Algebras and Polylogarithm Relations, the SIR Model, and a few Applied Math/Machine Learning topics revolving around dimensionality reduction of molecular interactions.</p> </li> <li> <p>2:00 - 4:00 PM: After the Math REU talks, I went back to IRB and met up with the rest of my group. We each discussed presentation plans (AF finished her slides and XG says he’ll work on them tomorrow before our meeting with our advisor), our research progress, and what we anticipate discussing with our advisor tomorrow. In terms of my SEGA approach, after I noticed the seed problem, the results are better but still don’t work as nicely as I would like – the guided images have pretty much everyone as the same race, which is not what we are looking for in terms of fair representation. I do think that we have good progress to show on this front and am excited to hear what my advisor thinks/has to say tomorrow.</p> </li> </ul> <p>I stayed a bit longer after research to listen to the Parallel Algorithms Group (PM, MA, AB) run through their presentation. Afterwards, I grabbed some CFA and scarfed it down for dinner before heading out with XG, SS, DS, and LH to Karoake in DC. We met up with the other group (PM driving SK, ZS, MA, AZ, and AB) and had a really good time at the Karoake place. I do think that certain people were pushing a bit hard on the songs they wanted to sing without thinking much about what others wanted, and certain people definitely enjoyed the Karoake more than others, but it was overall a fun time. After the drive back, I relaxed, did some coding, and prepared a bit for our meeting tomorrow. Big day tomorrow – and it will be a long one too. After research we’ll jump into our meeting (4-5) and then there is an REU Board Game night, which should be a good way to decompress after the meeting.</p> <h4 id="day-60-august-3rd-"><u>Day 60 (August 3rd) </u></h4> <p>Week 9 Day 4: Meeting #6</p> <ul> <li> <p>8:30 - 9:00 AM: No morning exercise today – I woke up pretty tired and my stomach hurt a bit so I just got a bit of extra sleep. Today was geared up to be a big day – Sherry is coming to visit for a few days, starting today, and we also have a meeting with our advisor after research.</p> </li> <li> <p>10:00 AM - 12:00 PM: In the morning, I once again worked alone for a bit. AF is out for the next few days, SS came in a bit late, and XG came in even later. I can’t really control anyone else’s effort besides myself but I feel a bit bummed since I want to have a good final push in the REU, especially with the presentation and important meetings coming up. I talked to XG a bit about his RL approach – it’s a bit of a work in progress but he’s done some good conceptual work to support it thus far – before working more on the presentation for our meeting and generating more pictures for individual and group fairness of both firefighters and teachers.</p> </li> <li> <p>12:00 - 1:00 PM: Sherry took a Lyft from her apartment to College Park – after some searching, I found her near STAMP, we dropped off her stuff in my room, and then went out for lunch. It was really great to see her again and I’m happy she’ll be staying for the next few days. We met up with a large portion of the REU back in IRB, where I introduced her to the other students, and ate our lunch.</p> </li> <li> <p>1:00 - 4:00 PM: There are a lot of group presentations happening right now – Bill told the groups to bring a “friend” to the practice talks (where Clyde Kruskal is going to provide feedback on our presentations) so they can give advice about how to make it better. DS explained the Comp Geo presentation to me yesterday night, so I didn’t want to double dip and listen in when I could be working. XG and SS decided to tag along (which is totally fine, especially since they haven’t seen the presentation before), and this meant that I was working alone again for much of the afternoon. I invited Sherry and LH to our normal room and I did a few practice run throughs of my presentation before working further on group fairness. I didn’t end up seeing SS or XG until near 4, when we went over to our advisor’s office for our meeting.</p> </li> <li> <p>4:00 - 5:30 PM: The meeting with our advisor went fine. She had a lot of feedback about our approaches and the general presentation (we presented a draft of our final presentation, which we’ll also be presenting in front of Clyde next Monday when AF is back), especially since it has been a while since our last official meeting (we sent updates but she was out for the ICML conference so I imagine she wasn’t able to read/understand much). We each presented what we were working on – I got a number of comments/questions about the Semantic Guidance approach, which she seemed to be on board with. After SS, XG, and AF (who was Zooming in) explained their respective approaches, we talked about next steps. My advisor thought the modified images were quite good and that Semantic Guidance is quite powerful (adjusting just the guided concepts), and wanted to understand the Semantic Guidance process and the math behind it more. This makes a lot of sense – in the next few days, I will also look into more of the math behind semantic guidance while improving the final presentation. Another idea she wanted me to think about is combining SS’s concept erasure approach with <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2304.03916.pdf">another approach</a> she saw at ICML – instead of freezing the entire diffusion model for concept erasure, we can freeze all but a few layers and fine tune those layers to lead to better guidance. This may be a more elegant approach than Semantic Guidance, considering Semantic Guidance moreso is a postprocessing step that modifies the output rather than the diffusion model itself. She also mentioned to keep in constant contact with her throughout this last week, and I think it will be good to finish strong and perhaps build on the project in the fall if all goes well.</p> </li> </ul> <p>After the meeting, I joined up with a large contingent of the REU for another Board Game night. The catering option was Medditeranean today, and I quickly ate that before moving on to play DiXit with Sherry, PM, MA, SS, LH, and a grad student. We moved on to a few hectic but fun games of Mafia before calling it a night. It was definitely a super long day but really fun overall, and it was especially highlighted by the fact that I got/get to see/be around Sherry again after not seeing her for the last few months! Hoping that tomorrow is a productive and fun Friday, which will wrap up the 9th (wow!) week of the program.</p> <h4 id="day-61-august-4th-"><u>Day 61 (August 4th) </u></h4> <p>Week 9 Day 5: End of Week 9</p> <ul> <li> <p>8:30 - 9:00 AM: Felt quite tired this morning so slept in to get some extra rest. I did wake up to a flurry of texts – it turns out a good third of the REU went out to the DC Waterfront area and messed around until 3 AM. This made me feel great about my decision to not go out yesterday night – I was already feeling pretty tired despite sleeping around midnight.</p> </li> <li> <p>10:00 AM - 12:00 PM: XG and SS messaged me that they were going to work from home yesterday early in the morning (they ended up going to DC), so it was just me and Sherry in IRB in the morning. As I wrote about yesterday, I read over the Semantic Guidance paper more closely, paying attention to the mathematical reasoning and the general framework. After the first read through, I didn’t get much more intuition behind the math, so I switched over to working a bit on the presentation slides to close out the morning.</p> </li> <li> <p>12:00 - 1:30 PM: Sherry and I walked over to IRB where we met up with more of the REU – I haven’t been feeling too hungry lately and managed to eat only half my pizza. After lunch, we went to the bookstore to look around and contemplate what to spend my extra meal money on (we ended up getting a small notebook for herand a pencil case for me).</p> </li> <li> <p>1:30 - 4:00 PM: XG didn’t show up for lunch and it seemed like SS was going to join a larger group to play Jackbox, so I decided to work from home in the afternoon after dropping off the leftover pizza in the fridge. I continued to read through the SEGA paper again – it seems like they use noise estimates to provide the semantic control/guidance – but the math is quite heavy and not terribly motivated. I’m hoping to get a solid grasp by Monday and to meet with my advisor then to discuss.</p> </li> </ul> <p>I felt quite tired in the afternoon so I took a nap, before working on some CodeForces and then heading out with Sherry for a run. We did a nice 2 mile loop around campus and walked the remainder of the distance to Pho Thom to enjoy a nice dinner. We grabbed some Kung Fu Tea on the way back before chilling out for the night. I think I’ll try to play some tennis with Sherry tomorrow and maybe have some meals with the others.</p> <h4 id="day-62-august-5th"><u>Day 62 (August 5th)</u></h4> <p>Week 9 Day 6: The End is Near</p> <p>After another average night of sleep (I woke up a few times, including at around 3 AM when it sounded like people were coming back/brushing their teeth to head to sleep, along with a few times in the morning), I woke up around 9 AM and got ready to head out to play some tennis with Sherry. As has been the case the last few weeks, there are typically at least two rackets to borrow from the gym, but today I was only able to get one racket, which meant that the tennis we were expecting probably wouldn’t happen. When we got to the courts, we found a large group with six rackets, and two or three of them were just not being used. We asked to borrow them and they agreed, so we got to hit around until the group left and we were once again left with just one racket. Luckily, we were saved by another group of players who had a few extra rackets and agreed to lend us one. The racket itself looked pretty professional so I made sure to not do any crazy hits/try to scrape the racket. Overall, the tennis itself was pretty fun and it was great to hit around with Sherry!</p> <p>For lunch, we decided to head over to Aroy Thai, which was recommended to us by LH. Sherry has said that eating with the large group is a lot, since they are quite loud, so we decided to invite just LH to lunch with us. It was good to catch up with her (and hear about the larger REU group’s adventures over the last few days) while enjoying some yummy Thai food.</p> <p>In the afternoon, I took a look at problems from this morning’s CodeForces contest. A and B were relatively simple and I got them pretty quickly (I would have placed between 3000th and 5000th with just my performance on the first two problems in practice, which would be a strong performance relative to my rating), but C looked harder and I want to spend some time working on it later. Sherry and I attempted to check out the bookstore to see what merch we could get with my (still) extra money, but the bookstore closed before we could really find anything.</p> <p>We went out for an evening run afterwards – this time to make sure Sherry secured the Course Record on the McKeldin Loop segment (I ended up crushing a 6:45 mile after pacing her for the first 800), and then walked over to Playa Bowls to enjoy a light dinner. We came back, relaxed and finished the rest of our leftover pizza, before calling it a night. It was definitely a fun time today – she is leaving tomorrow which will be sad but I’m glad and proud that she’s getting ready for the start of her new job on Monday!</p> <h4 id="day-63-august-6th-"><u>Day 63 (August 6th) </u></h4> <p>Week 9 Day 7: The End of Week 9</p> <p>Sherry and I decided to wake up a bit earlier in hopes of grabbing breakfast before she left. After taking a look at the place we were thinking of going to yesterday (The Common), we noticed that there wasn’t many breakfast options, so we ended up walking to Starbucks and enjoying some coffee and breakfast sandwiches. After coming back to pack some more (I gave her my yoga mat and a rice cooker to bring back), I called an Uber back for her and she went over to her apartment to prep for her starting her job tomorrow!</p> <p>I mainly relaxed for the afternoon – I ended up just having some Graham Crackers for “lunch” since no one seemed to want to head out for a group lunch. After lunch, DS, AB, and I organized a group 800m race around the Quad, with PM and LH watching. I unfortunately finished 2nd, finishing behind DS and getting dusted in the last 50 meters… that being said, we were definitely finished around 2:30ish (at least that’s what it felt like) so we were definitely moving. Since I had agreed to go on a group run with AB, our suite (DS, AB, ML, and I) immediately went for a longer run after the race – I was absolutely gassed so I ended up struggling through the first mile before calling it a day.</p> <p>For dinner, I went out to eat with AF, LH, SK, DS, and we met up with MA at Hanami, a Japanese restaurant. I enjoyed a Chicken Teriyaki Bowl (the portion size was kind of small but it tasted alright) and grabbed some pictures (as I do every time we go out). To close out the night, I worked a bit on our presentation before calling it.</p> <p>It’s been a crazy nine weeks – just one more and the program’s over. I hope we finish strong research-wise with a great presentation and that we continue to build on our existing approaches… socially, I hope we all enjoy the last bit of time we have as this year’s REU group!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="caar"/><category term="research"/><category term="cs"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Week 9 of my Summer 2023 experience @ REU-CAAR.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">REU-CAAR, Week 8</title><link href="https://dyang5.github.io/blog/2023/REUCAAR-week8/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="REU-CAAR, Week 8"/><published>2023-07-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://dyang5.github.io/blog/2023/REUCAAR-week8</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://dyang5.github.io/blog/2023/REUCAAR-week8/"><![CDATA[<h4 id="day-50-july-24th"><u>Day 50 (July 24th)</u></h4> <p>Week 8 Day 1: 50 Days</p> <ul> <li>8:30 - 9:00 AM: It’s crazy to think that I’ve been here for 50 days already. We now officially have just three weeks (more like two since the final presentation will be sometime during the last week), so hopefully my group can finalize some presentable results in the next two weeks (I feel good about the way my new Semantic Guidance approach is going).</li> </ul> <p>I’ve been a bit lazier than I would like to be with regards to Monday and Friday workouts; from my experience, these are the days when the lane lines at the pools are being moved, and my pool workouts usually get cut in half because of this. I had planned to wake up at 8:30 to go on a morning run, but upon waking up, I made the decision to take the extra hour of sleep; as I figured out later, this may have made me more tired.</p> <ul> <li> <p>10:00 AM - 12:00 PM: With the program ending soon and our advisor out in Hawaii for a big ML conference, it is really go time for our group, and it’s kind of up to us to get as much done as we can. XG said he wasn’t feeling good and couldn’t make it in today, so it was me, SS, and AF holding down the fort. Continuing off my work from last week, I have been working on an approach that uses Semantic Guidance for fair image generation. This morning, I focused a bit more on actually getting individual fairness to work, and the success was noticeable, which is great! Though the approach for individual fairness is very similar to the one presented in the following <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.10893.pdf">Fair Diffusion</a> paper (hence why we want to focus on group fairness in this project), it is good to see some progress being made and for the images to be generally more fair.</p> </li> <li> <p>12:00 - 1:30 PM: We had another Monday lunch talk hosted by Professor Jon Katz of UMD CS. Though Bill titled the talk as “Security and Crypto,” the talk ended up being more about Jon’s experience working in industry and academia. The talk itself was quite insightful, and I was reminded of how, just like in previous weeks, I’ve felt like all these speakers, whether they are tenured professors or industry people, are all very well-spoken as well as knowledgable. From a personal perspective, there’s a lot to consider when applying to grad programs, but if I can matched up with advisors like these speakers, I think I’ll be in a good spot (by the way, if you’re a professor of mine reading this due to some of the emails I sent out recently, hello!).</p> </li> <li> <p>1:30 - 4:00 PM: The next step in the semantic guidance approach is to work on solving the problem of group fairness. My idea is to use the results of the gender and race classifier I was working with previously (DeepFace), especially the classification confidences, to weight the guidance of each photo. At its current state, if we give a guidance prompt like “middle eastern” to get the people in an image to look more middle eastern, every person will become more middle eastern. Consequently, I’m hoping that if I can use the “average” confidences (in terms of race and gender) to support the semantic guidance across an entire image, the overall output can be more fair than the original generated one. (Note that the guidance is sort of inversely proportional to overall confidence – if the classifier is very sure that the people in the image are white, then ideally the generated image will have greater representation of other races). In the afternoon, I started setting up (using previous code I’ve written) a pipeline to generate an image, classify the people in the image, get the gender/race confidences, and use that to “guide” a more fair image – I’m hoping the results will be successful but at the very least, I’m happy that I’m beginning to work on an approach that I’m much more enthusiastic/excited about compared to before.</p> </li> </ul> <p>After research, I went down to the second floor to pick up a check for my last few weeks of research. I then walked back to the dorm, felt quite tired, and proceeded to take a much-longer-than-anticipated nap. I had originally planned to head to the pool after research but I didn’t think I would make it back to the Student Union by 7 if I did do that, so I ended up going for a pretty breezy 2 mile run around campus. Grabbing some CFA from STAMP, I went back, ate dinner, worked on some CodeForces (I finished up 1850H, which means that I’ve now “solved all” – missing A, B, and C which are typically much easier– of the problems from the most recent Div 4, which is the first contest I’ve fully solved), and did some laundry to close out the night.</p> <p>#### <u>Day 51 (July 25th)</u></p> <p>Week 8 Day 2</p> <ul> <li> <p>8:30 - 9:00 AM: Back to the morning swims I go! I was really not feeling it this morning – despite the nap I took yesterday evening and a solid 8ish hours of sleep, I was feeling tired and my arms felt like jelly. I managed to push through for 25ish minutes of swimming and finished with around 40 laps.</p> </li> <li> <p>10:00 AM - 12:00 PM: Continuing my work from yesterday, my goal today was to build on the Semantic Guidance approach using results from the DeepFace gender/race classifier. After taking some time to set up the relevant analysis (reading the classifier results and storing it in a dictionary, then looping through the dictionary to get the average confidence), I took a while to think about how I could weight the guidance based on the average confidence. My first idea, however, turned out hilariously bad, with the resulting images getting completely changed by the edit guidance weights/hyperparameters. I had a good laugh with XG, SS, and AF about how bad the results were, and then went back to thinking about how I could make the guidance a bit better (more thinking is needed on this front).</p> </li> <li> <p>1:15 - 4:00 PM: In the afternoon session, I built on my work from the morning. After a bit more experimentation and generation yielded slightly better but not by much results (images were a bit more clear than the morning but the faces/people looked nothing like the original images), I decided to refrain from guiding race and gender with prompting and instead focus on just guiding gender (male or female). Using similar ideas with the average confidence, I generated a few slightly better images. LH joined us in our conference room, and so SS, LH, and I got sidetracked talking about grad school expectations, life, and applications – these conversations, though they kind of distract us from research for a bit, are in my opinion really insightful and rewarding, and I’m glad that they are happy to just chat so openly and honestly. This is one of the aspects I like the most about an REU compared to research at Swarthmore – since we all live close together, are part of the same program, and come from different backgrounds/schools, it’s easier to have a honest conversation with different perspectives, and I’m really grateful for that. In terms of research, I think the SEGA approach I’ve been working on still has some serious promise, which is great.</p> </li> </ul> <p>I’ve been feeling quite tired after research, so I mainly relaxed until 6, when I decided to go do laundry, grab CFA for dinner, and then move my clothes from the washer to the dryer. I came back, did some quick CodeForces, reading, and more relaxing. I like hanging out with the other REU students but it’s always good to have some days of solo time to decompress. A few of us were initially planning to watch a movie at night but LH had a headache, so we’ll have to wait another day for that.</p> <h4 id="day-52-july-26th"><u>Day 52 (July 26th)</u></h4> <p>Week 8 Day 3</p> <ul> <li> <p>8:30 - 9:00 AM: I woke up today to some stomach problems – my stomach didn’t feel great when I went to sleep yesterday and these problems continued a bit into the morning. This is my second time in as many weeks with stomach problems, so I was kinda concerned about this. Instead of risking anything, I decided to skip on a morning swim or run; though I have really wanted to be consistent with my exercise, I didn’t think that exacerbating potential stomach issues would be worth it.</p> </li> <li> <p>10:00 AM - 12:00 PM: My main worry in the morning was making sure my stomach issue would go away. I called my dad before research and he advised me to get it checked with a doctor, so I quickly got an appointment for later that afternoon. Similarly, I asked AF to bring some Pepto Bismal to IRB and she clutched up on that front; however, the pepto didn’t really seem to do the trick. After the issues subsided slightly, I discussed my SEGA approach and what I was working on figuring out (a good way to modify the edit weights to get the distribution of male and female identified images to be close to 50-50) with AF and SS to hear their suggestions/thoughts. After some further discussion, I think we came to the consensus that the current SEGA approach is related to the Fair Diffusion paper (mentioned above) and the <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.00070">Debiasing via Biased Prompts</a> paper (one of the other papers we read very on in the research process). Though parts of my current approach, like running an additional classification to determine the proper guidance weights, are costly in terms of generation time and may not be as effective as the Debiasing paper, I still think it’s worthwhile to continue working on my approach to get something working. I am a firm believer in first getting an approach to work and then improving it, so I think I’ll continue to do that – and after the REU ends, we may want to look further into the Debiasing paper’s approach and apply their work to group fairness.</p> </li> <li> <p>1:00 - 1:15 PM: I had a quick appointment at the UMD Health Center to talk about my stomach issues – the doctor gave me some advice and mainly said that he didn’t think it was too serious (and told me to get another appointment if the issues keep recurring), which is good to hear. In the remaining twoish weeks, I’ll be sure to more closely look out for the food I’m eating…</p> </li> <li> <p>1:30 - 4:00 PM: I quickly grabbed some lunch before heading back to IRB to work in our afternoon research session. PM and MA came to our room and we talked a bit about our research, before they dispersed and we got back to working on our project. I talked to SS and AF a bit more, extending the discussion we had in the morning, about how we might use the confidence estimates from our classifier to get proper guidance weights – in the remaining time, I began implementing the first of the approaches we talked about, before running into out of memory errors caused by CUDA (so I will run these again tomorrow). Since I’ve just been experimenting, I’ve only been generating three images at a time but I imagine I’ll need to generate a lot more to get a better sense of whether or not the distribution of male-female generated images is balanced.</p> </li> </ul> <p>After research, I took a bit of a break before heading out to play some soccer with NL, PM, MA, and SS. I went to STAMP to get some CFA and had dinner with LH, with SS and AF joining later. She talked a bit about trying to get SWE internships next year and we talked a bit about a Sliding Windows Leetcode problem she was thinking about, which was fun. I think it’s really fun to be able to connect to some of these REU students; for the younger ones, I’ve been telling them that I’d love to be able to help them in any way I can, especially since I wish I had some mentorship or upperclassmen friends to talk with when I was just starting out at Swarthmore. So for anyone who’s younger (or older) and may be curious about anything/want guidance, feel free to reach out!</p> <p>I went for a late-night run around the Main Quad to get some extra exercise for the day – this felt great and I didn’t feel any stomach issues, so I was quite happy about that.</p> <h4 id="day-53-july-27th"><u>Day 53 (July 27th)</u></h4> <p>Week 8 Day 4: Stomachache</p> <ul> <li> <p>8:30 - 9:00 AM: Woke up in the morning and to put it simply, stomach felt terrible. The pain was a bit different from previous days though – it’s closer to the chest area and more of a nagging rather than a off-and-on-cramping. I decided to get some extra sleep and not risk any strenuous activity.</p> </li> <li> <p>10:00 AM - 12:00 PM: Really not much to report here, research wise. I was not feeling good after waking up and decided to work from home. This mainly meant staying in bed and grabbing at my stomach. The few tests I tried to run ended up getting CUDA out of memory errors…</p> </li> <li> <p>1:00 PM - 2:30 PM: I grabbed some lunch from PE and met up with the other REU students eating at STAMP. Lunch didn’t go too well either with me feeling quite out of it and my stomach still hurting. I attempted to head back to IRB and work there but at around 2:30 decided against working for longer and went back to the dorm to sleep.</p> </li> <li> <p>4:00 - 5:00 PM: I had intended on going to Emily Kaplitz’s talk on “Neurodiversity” but my stomach didn’t feel good enough to make the walk over to the Math building. I heard the talk was great so it sucks that two of the talks I’ve wanted to go to the most (Emily’s and Evan’s) are the only ones I’ve missed.</p> </li> </ul> <p>After “research” today, I carried up six (!) 40 packs of water my parents ordered from Costco for me, grabbed dinner at CFA (but got a healthier wrap today due to stomach pain) and talked briefly with AB, LH, and SS. To get my mind off my stomach and jumping in bed (laying down kind of hurts my stomach), I agreed to go to the library to work with LH and AF. After leaving the library when it closed and some more debugging, I managed to get the CodeForces problem I was working on, so that’s probably the highlight of my day. I think if my stomach still hurts tomorrow, I’ll get another appointment with the doctor… this is probably the worst stretch of the REU thus far so sorry for any new readers who have to read through this stretch…</p> <h4 id="day-54-july-28th"><u>Day 54 (July 28th)</u></h4> <p>Week 8 Day 5: Recovery</p> <ul> <li> <p>8:30 - 9:00 AM: No morning swim or run today – just trying to recover fully. I slept with my head on an incline (padded more pillows) and my stomach felt a lot better than when I woke up yesterday (whether or not that is related, who knows).</p> </li> <li> <p>10:00 AM - 12:00 PM: I told my group members that I would likely be working from home again today since I didn’t feel fully recovered. The pain was still there throughout the morning as well, which made me a bit concerned. Research wise, XG reported that his Reinforcement Learning approach was looking promising, which is great. I tried to run my code, got a few out of memory errors, and so I decided to work on a general Python file that will generate images with the proper prompts instead of working in my typical Jupyter Notebooks. Afterwards, I moved on and began working on my group’s final presentation, which we’re making in Beamer.</p> </li> <li> <p>1:00 - 1:30 PM: I decided to get another doctor’s appointment since my stomach pain symptoms were a bit different than the ones on Wednesday. The doctor didn’t seem to think the pain was any serious, long-term problem, which was good to hear. I think I will just have to be more careful about what I eat and I think this stomach pain is likely due to some continuation of the effects from last week’s.</p> </li> <li> <p>1:30 - 4:00 PM: In the afternoon, I kept working on the final presentation slides. I made a slide outlining the presentation and began working on the background/motivation slides. I think I will need to do a slightly better job of explaining the basics of a diffusion model, but the presentation making has been relatively easy so far since we already have a few good baseline slides from our group presentations.</p> </li> </ul> <p>Post-research, I took a nap before heading over to CVS to get some of the over-the-counter medication the doctor recommended. After walking back to drop off the medication (and some Gatorade), I quickly showered and met SK, SS, CD (one of last year’s students visiting), AF, and LH outside to take an Uber to Taqueria Habanero. We got a nice dinner and due to some heavy rain and thunder outside, decided to Uber back. It’s always good to talk and hang out with the other REU students – the best part of it was that my stomach was and has been feeling a lot better. Fingers crossed it stays feeling good throughout the remainder of the REU!</p> <h4 id="day-55-july-29th"><u>Day 55 (July 29th)</u></h4> <p>Week 8 Day 6: Weekend Recovery pt. 1</p> <ul> <li>10:30 AM - 1:00 PM: My big goal this weekend is to recover well from all the stomach pain I’ve been having. After a good night’s rest, I woke up this morning and decided to enter in the CodeForces content being hosted. At the start of the REU, my goal was to keep practicing (at least a problem a day) and to enter in as many competition as I could, and I’ve been doing this to varying success (I’ve been doing my daily problems but haven’t been doing the competitions as seriously as I would have liked). Despite a subpar performance (solving A in 3 minutes, B in 45ish minutes, and then not getting C1 – a difficult but doable problem), I’m happy to have at least participated in the contest formally, which is my first formal participation since the REU.</li> </ul> <p>After the contest, I made myself some scraps for lunch. This included a mumbo jumbo of all the food my parents ordered for me due to my stomachaches, including Bananas, Graham Crackers, and Ramen/Noodles. I then upsolved C1 after understanding the solution and mainly lounged around until dinner. There was a rough thunderstorm outside, so I had some noodles and a banana for dinner.</p> <p>No stomachache so far, so it’s already a good day considering how I’ve been feeling lately. My parents told me to lay low on heavy exercise for a bit so no running or swimming again today (the bad weather out made other sports a no-go too).</p> <p>After dinner, AB, DS, LH and I “watched” the movie “My Dinner with Andre.” I got kind of lost in the beginning and didn’t pay too much attention after a bit, but I thought the overall message was quite nice (in my opinion, to generally enjoy the little things in life).</p> <h4 id="day-56-july-30th"><u>Day 56 (July 30th)</u></h4> <p>The End of Week 8: Two to Go</p> <p>It was an eventful morning today – after initially waking up at 8 and hearing that some of LH’s friends (who we were scheduled to meet) were delayed in traffic, I decided to go back to sleep to get an extra thirty minutes of sleep. After waking up, I showered and got ready to meet her friends, grad students studying in the US at Yale, Caltech, and UChicago that she knows from her high school in Vietnam. After some parking problems (we did not know the nearest available parking), we finally met and subsequently decided to head directly to the movie theater. This involved corraling AF and SK out of their suite about 10-15 minutes earlier than expected, so that we could head out on an Uber to the Regal movie theater to watch Oppenheimer. Oppenheimer itself was a great movie – I very much enjoyed it but also thought it was funny that from about halfway onwards, one of my main thoughts was to hold it in and not use the bathroom (not thinking about using the bathroom for the last thirty minutes turned out to help tremendously). After Oppenheimer, we walked around Silver Springs, MD (where the movie theater was) and decided to head to a nearby sushi place for lunch. AF, SK, and I then Ubered back to let LH hang out some more with her friends on her own. For dinner, I made noodles and ramen for the third time in two days. Post-dinner, DS, AB, SS, and I played some board games in the basement before retiring for the night.</p> <p>We now really only have 2 (or a week and a half of actual research time) left in the program. I feel like any research progress we can eke out now is incremental, so I’ve been trying to make the most of the time I have left with everyone before we disperse into our respective collegs and out into the world again…</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="caar"/><category term="research"/><category term="cs"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Week 8 of my Summer 2023 experience @ REU-CAAR.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">REU-CAAR, Week 7</title><link href="https://dyang5.github.io/blog/2023/REUCAAR-week7/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="REU-CAAR, Week 7"/><published>2023-07-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://dyang5.github.io/blog/2023/REUCAAR-week7</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://dyang5.github.io/blog/2023/REUCAAR-week7/"><![CDATA[<h4 id="day-43-july-17th"><u>Day 43 (July 17th)</u></h4> <p>Week 7, Day 1</p> <ul> <li> <p>8:30 - 9:00 AM: Wow. It’s week 7 already, which is crazy. Time is dwindling – I hope we get some cool research results to present in just under three weeks. Instead of getting out for my Monday morning swim, I played it safe and waited for AG, the grad lead for REU-CAAR, to bring all the isolating students COVID Test Kits (which is quite nice of him). I tested Negative and so that meant I could finally get back to work at IRB. I broughout out my mask just to be safe as well.</p> </li> <li> <p>10:00 AM - 12:00 PM: To start off the research week, I wanted to work on testing the results from the generated images (from our diffusion models) on the DeepFace classifier. After some experimentation with prompting and comparing the results to work from my other group members, I generated 15 images for each of the four types of prompts (portrait/group images of doctors/firefighters) and proceeded to hand-label the portrait images. I then used the image to classification pipeline that I had written from previous weeks, modified some of the code, and ran it on the generated images. To analyze the results, I would need to hand-label the images (since they are generated and are not part of a labeled dataset). After some discussion with my group, I ended up doing this for the portrait images before heading to lunch.</p> </li> <li> <p>12:00 - 1:30 PM: We had another one of our weekly Monday REU lunch talks. Today Bill gave a talk on <a href="https://www.cs.umd.edu/~gasarch/REU/hatstalk.pdf">The Hat Problem</a>. I had seen this problem before but did not remember the strategy (and I also had not seen the many extensions proposed by Bill); overall, I found the talk quite enjoyable and it was great to think mathematically/problem-solve for the first time in a while. I definitely want to ask Bill whether I can present a version of this to professors at Swarthmore, or even present it as part of the IMC (Interactive Math Colloquium) Club I run, since I very much enjoyed this talk!</p> </li> <li> <p>1:30 - 4:00 PM: I quite enjoyed Bill’s Hat Talk so I spent some time afterwards discussing the proofs (especially the infinite hat, 2 colors and infinite hat, at most 1 error cases) with AF and SS (XG, our final group member, is going to be working remotely this week). We talked a bit about the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Axiom_of_choice">Axiom of Choice</a>, our thoughts on it, as well as some resulting paradoxes including Banach–Tarski (the Axiom of Choice is used in one of the proofs discussed by Bill). Afterwards, I ended up discussing the general research plan (what everyone was working on, potential limitations of our research and what we can do to address them, and what we can do next to get a solid research project before the REU ends) with my group members AF and SS. I think this was really productive – at times, I feel like I’ve only been working on a small part of the pipeline, but it’s important to realize that the general fairness process we are trying to build relies on many different small but essential parts. AF and I also tried to reason through mathematical foundation behind a Latent Diffusion Model paper SS was trying to read through, to some success. I didn’t get too much done outside of this group discussion, but I feel like having these sorts of discussions is really necessary to get everyone aligned and on the same page and to build a solid working dynamic, so I was quite happy with that.</p> </li> </ul> <p>After research, I ended up relaxing a bit before heading out to “play badminton” with ZF, AG, and SS. It turns out there were only 3 badminton racquets, and since I didn’t want them to have to rotate, I ended up playing Racquetball on my own for 30ish minutes. Afterwards, I waited around and watched them and others play badminton. This ended up taking much longer than anticipated, which I was okay with since I mainly was on my phone after a while, but it meant that we had to jog to CFA before it closed at 7. Obviously, then, since we ordered right before closing, the food wasn’t as good as normal. Oh well.</p> <p>Outside of research, I’ve been waiting for my monitor to arrive (it was supposed to arrive yesterday but the delivery didn’t go through), and it hasn’t arrived yet today, either, which kind of sucks. I’m really looking forward to a better setup to hopefully allow me to be more productive and work easier in my room. I’ve also been waiting to hear from the <a href="https://ymc.osu.edu/">Young Mathematicians Conference</a>, a math conference I applied to using my work from last year, so fingers crossed on that front!</p> <h4 id="day-44-july-18th"><u>Day 44 (July 18th)</u></h4> <p>Week 7, Day 2</p> <ul> <li> <p>8:30 - 9:00 AM: I had planned to exercise outside yesterday (swim or run) and in the morning today, but we hit another wave of bad air quality (I think this is the third one in this REU program alone, with 130+ AQI, meaning the Air Quality is unhealthy for outdoor activity). When I woke up at 6:30 AM to check on the AQI, it was still Unhealthy, so I set my alarms for 9 to get an extra hour of sleep.</p> </li> <li> <p>10:00 AM - 12:00 PM: Over the last few days, I’ve been focused on trying to get good diffusion model output as well as trying to test the DeepFace classifier on the generated output. For the latter part, I have everything I need to do this (I would need to write a bit more code to do so but it wouldn’t take too long), but I have been putting it off. My reasoning for this is twofold: many of the generated group images have terrible image quality (faces are deformed), making labeling and comparing to the results from the classifier difficult/not useful. Furthermore, even for the single images (one person in an image), the hand-labeling of a person’s race is very subjective and thus it’s difficult to accurately analyze the classifier. As a result, I’ve moved away from this and have thought more about how we can get fair image generation. One of our current projects, led by AF, is Domain Translation, which involves masking a certain part of an image (e.g. one person) and using a Blended Latent Diffusion model to “translate” that person’s gender or race. For example, one can mask a man and say “change this person to a woman.” Ideally, this person would look very similar characteristic wise as to what the original person is wearing, since the model tries to “blend” the result into the rest of the image. Through some initial experiments, this has been unsuccessful/difficult. As a result, I’ve been looking into some work that follows a <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.12247.pdf">Semantic Guidance</a> paper, where given an image and a concept, the concept is added/suppressed in the image while preserving the other characteristics of an image.</p> </li> <li> <p>1:00 - 4:00 PM: In the morning, I read a bit about the paper and the general process before starting to implement the code from the <a href="https://colab.research.google.com/github/ml-research/semantic-image-editing/blob/main/examples/SemanticGuidance.ipynb#scrollTo=4e6e6724">Semantic Guidance Colab</a> locally. I got this working and started looking at generating group images and how guidance on gender/race would affect the image. Tomorrow, I want to try to combine our existing domain translation approach (where a certain part of the image is masked) and the Semantic Guidance approach. My (maybe optimistic) hope is to be able to mask a certain part of the image, guide that part of the image, and “stitch” the resulting parts together to lead to a fair outcome, as this will preserve general background characteristics in a generated image while making the image more fair. We closed the day by talking a bit as a group, and we somehow ended up working on some math problems from China’s famous Gaokao examination (which was fun) as well.</p> </li> </ul> <p>After research, I headed to the gym to play basketball with PM, MA, AB, SS, and DS before joining AG and ZS at the pool afterwards. We mainly messed around at the pool (there was so many people and the lanes were all packed), which included me and ZS attempting to teach SS how to dive into a pool as well as going on the slide/diving boards. I also briefly swam a few laps near the end, when lanes started to free up. I got home back around 8 PM, warmed up some leftover pizza, did some CodeForces, and that was that.</p> <p>For some non-research related content, I had to cancel my monitor shipment from Amazon today, since it has not been delivered despite remaining at the Amazon facilities. This kind of sucks since I was hoping to work on a monitor for the remainder of the REU (and I will hand it off to Sherry post research for her to use in industry). On the plus side, I found out today I was accepted as a Report Presenter at this year’s YMC (Young Mathematicians Conference), which I am quite happy about! I guess maybe not getting a monitor for now is a small price to pay for getting accepted into YMC. :)</p> <h4 id="day-45-july-19th"><u>Day 45 (July 19th)</u></h4> <p>Week 7, Day 3</p> <ul> <li> <p>8:30 - 9:00 AM: AQI is back to normal and I’m out of isolation so there are no excuses for not going for a morning swim now! I, admittedly reluctantly, got out of bed and over to the pool for a quick 25 minute, 40 lap swim. It’s good to get back to lap swimming and hopefully I’ll get back into the groove of things quickly.</p> </li> <li> <p>10:00 AM - 12:00 PM: In the morning, I experimented a bit more with the Semantic Guidance Pipeline from diffusers, specifically the prompt manipulation which leads to a different generated image. A minor yet useful adjustment I made was displaying multiple images in a grid-like fashion, so I can compare the results before/after each guidance stage and compare it to the original image output. It seems like there’s a difference between guiding “male” and reverse-guiding “female,” so we may need to think about which one we want if there is an abundance of one gender (for example, guiding “male” may generate a few men in places where the original image had no person – this may not be desirable).</p> </li> <li> <p>1:00 - 4:00 PM: I started to test the Semantic Guidance pipeline a bit more on group images. I think I will need to tinker around more with the other hyperparameters (including the number of editing steps, guidance strength, edit momentum, etc.) to get a handle of the parameters we would want to use to lead to more fair image generation. Adding the reverse prompting of “deformed, blurry, …” and other negative prompts I used in stable diffusion experimentation led to slightly better quality images most of the time, but when I used these prompts without the additional guidance of a gender term, the model started generating almost exclusively people with darker skin and doctor hats on… which is weird. I’ll continue experimenting with this to see why this is the case. Also, I have been thinking that we will need to use Semantic Guidance in combination with a mask, but I don’t think this is the case anymore – especially if this alone can lead to more fair image generation for groups, which would itself be novel; the masking approach is more of a postprocessing than the one I am currently trying.</p> </li> </ul> <p>After research, I hung around in our work room to get a little bit more work done, type up this, and then head down for our second Board Game night of the REU. I started by joining a mini game of SET before starting a new game of Olympus with DS and Bill Gasarch, the program director. After a bit of a learning curve and Bill teaching us how to play, we successfully completed a game, with Bill finishing first with 51 points, me finishing second with 48, and DS finishing in last with 31 (which was hilarious since he was joking about how he wanted to finish ahead of me). In between, we paused for some catering from a nearby Indian place, which was much tastier than I had expected. I closed out the night by briefly playing some Poker and some Codenames with some graduate students as well as SS, AZ, DS, MA, LH, and ML.</p> <p>There is no meeting with our advisor this week since she is heading to Honolulu for <a href="https://icml.cc/">ICML (International Conference on Machine Learning)</a>, but we plan to update her on Slack with our weekly progress.</p> <h4 id="day-46-july-20th"><u>Day 46 (July 20th)</u></h4> <p>Week 7, Day 4</p> <ul> <li> <p>8:30 - 9:00 AM: Once again, I got out of bed reluctantly to head out for a morning swim. I have been sleeping closer to midnight these last few days and might have to sleep a bit earlier to be more energized for these swims… Anyways, I ended up going for 30 minutes and 50+ laps, which is great pace-wise especially considering I’m just coming back from a break due to isolation and bad air quality.</p> </li> <li> <p>10:00 AM - 12:00 PM: On Thursday mornings, we usually have grad meetings with my advisor’s group, but everyone is out for the previously mentioned ICML conference; as a result, the next two grad meetings are canceled. This means a bit more work time on Thursday mornings, and so today I continued to work a bit more on Semantic Guidance. I am hoping to solve individual fairness first (similar to other papers, like Fair Diffusion) but apply my own touch for the approach. As a result, I also spent some of the morning looking through the Fair Diffusion paper’s code and thinking about where I can extend their procedure/improve on it.</p> </li> <li> <p>1:30 - 4:00 PM: In the afternoon session, I generated and modified a few images using SEGA (Semantic Guidance) but mainly focused on writing an update for my mentor (our updates to her will take the place of our meeting this week). Here are my thoughts, split into 1) limitations of our project/approaches so far and 2) what I’ve been working on this week.</p> </li> </ul> <blockquote> <p>As we talked about in last week’s group meeting, we have been trying to think about some of the limitations of our current approaches. It is difficult to say how we can deal with them, but we are trying to answer them/keep them in mind as we work on our different approaches: &lt;li&gt;For the generative process, we find that stable diffusion generated images yield deformed/blurry faces for group images. Ideally, we want these to be higher quality/more human like (as this might make our classifiers more accurate resulting in higher fairness).&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;In our general pipeline, we acknowledge that our gender/race classifier (e.g. DeepFace) may itself be biased/faulty, yet it is a part of our general process for fair image generation.&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;We have not figured out how to separate fairness across different concepts (doctors and nurses). For example, if a generated image has 5 male doctors and 5 female nurses, our RL approach may deem this as a “fair image” when it is technically not.&lt;/li&gt;</p> </blockquote> <blockquote> <p>On the personal side, here’s a bit more about what I’m now working on: last week I tried experimenting with negative prompting in stable diffusion and completed prompt-to-image and image-to-classification pipelines. This week I’ve been focusing on experimenting with SEGA (“Semantic Guidance”), a technique that uses semantic guidance to “guide” diffusion model output. This is similar to the domain translator approach Amy has been working on, but the domain translator modifies the generated diffusion image, whereas SEGA guides the diffusion process by modifying vectors in the semantic space. My current goals for SEGA include getting fair image outputs over a batch for photos with just one person. To extend previous work, I hope to work more with the editing and guidance hyperparameters (for example, in group fairness, I may want to adjust the guidance scales based on the confidence of the race classifiers) as well as use gender and race classifiers to guide the editing process. In comparison, previous papers like Fair Diffusion support prompts of just one format “a photo of the face of a [occupation]” and the guidance is done manually by the user. Though I plan to start by working to solve individual person fairness, I hope to extend these ideas to group fairness as well.</p> </blockquote> <ul> <li>4:00 - 5:30 PM: I went to a talk by Professor Victor Yakovneko (Physics Professor at UMD) on “The Statistical Mechanics of Money.” The talk was about how the Boltzmann-Pareto distribution (which is typically used to describe the physics of objects in a system) can be similarly applied to monetary concepts such as income/tax flow. I thought the talk itself was pretty interesting, but it ended up going quite a bit over, which was bad since I really had to use the restroom.</li> </ul> <p>After research activities, I went straight to the gym to play basketball. MA and I arrived first, to no available balls and no available courts. After some clever finagling and asking around, we ended up with both a half-court to play on and a basketball, and so we got a game going with SK, SS, MA, PM, DS, and later, two other students. For dinner, SS let me have one of her Shin Ramen packs, and I had that along with some leftovers from PE from two days before. Afterwards, I showered up, confirmed my participation in YMC this year (yay!), and did some CodeForces to close out the night.</p> <h4 id="day-47-july-21st"><u>Day 47 (July 21st)</u></h4> <p>Final Work Day of Week 7!</p> <ul> <li> <p>8:30 - 9:00 AM: Snoozed my alarm today. My reasoning is that the lane lines are always shuffled on Friday mornings, which cuts my normal swimming time in half. Instead, I took the extra hour of sleep and planned to swim after research…</p> </li> <li> <p>10:00 - 12:00 PM: As I wrote previously, my goal has now shifted to solidfying the Semantic Guidance approach for individual fairness. Today, my main goal was to tinker with the hyperparameters to understand how each hyperparameter affects the generated diffusion image. In the morning, I worked on trying different prompts and thought about how I could incorporate classifier results into the hyperparameters (as a preliminary idea, I think I could make each race an editing prompt and set their relative strengths to 1 minus the relative confidence predictions for each race).</p> </li> <li> <p>1:00 - 4:00 PM: In the afternoon, I worked more on the hyperparameter tuning approach. I was planning to use GridSearchCV, which is an exhaustive hyperparameter approach I learned in Swat’s ML class that tries every combination of hyperparameters, but since I also want to visualize the results, I wanted to try something a bit easier. I ended up setting up the hyperparameter tests using two for loops, where the outer for loop represents the hyperparameter being changed (1 of 6) and the inner for loop represents the value it is changed to (1 of 4), with all other hyperparameters constant. I got some really weird results (some of the generated images look like noise + a bird even though the prompt is “a photo of the face of a doctor”) that I will need to parse more through.</p> </li> </ul> <p>After some serious morning planning, a bunch of us from the REU group went to the movie theaters to catch the premiere of Barbie &amp; Oppenheimer, with the group leaning towards wanting to watch Barbie… (I would have preferred Oppenheimer). I ended up taking an Uber with SS and AF, and PM drove MA, DS, JS, AZ to the 4:45 movie. I had no expectations for the Barbie movie but I thought it was relatively well-written, and the ending message was pretty nice. Afterwards, I went to The Spot Mini with MA, SS, AF, and AZ (bad idea bc my stomach hurt very bad afterwards) before grabbing my computer monitor (it finally arrived) from the nearby Amazon locker and heading home. 7 weeks are gone already… time flies.</p> <h4 id="day-48-july-22nd"><u>Day 48 (July 22nd)</u></h4> <p>Week 7, Day 6: No More Spot Mini</p> <p>I had a terrible end to the night yesterday with a bad stomachache from whatever I ate at The Spot Mini. I haven’t felt great after eating there before, but my stomach hasn’t felt that bad in a while. It was really hurting yesterday night, and so I went to sleep relatively early – it felt better as I was falling asleep. The stomachache definitely didn’t disappear since I woke up at 12:30 AM with a bad pain in my stomach. After texting AF and SS to ask if they had any Tylenol (so I could get some rest of the night), AF clutched up and gave me some Pepto Bismal, which is supposed to be for upset stomachaches. I felt a lot better after taking it and fell asleep shortly after near 1.</p> <p>My stomach felt much better when I woke up in the morning. I had initially planned to play tennis with AF and SS at 11 but wasn’t sure due to the complications yesterday night. Luckily, since I felt much better, I went out to play with AF (we normally play on Sundays but we have a REU hiking activity tomorrow which should be fun). Afterwards, I grabbed some PE, ran into SS and JS in line, and SS, AF, and I ate lunch together at the Union. I took a quick break (and nap) before I went out later in the afternoon to get some swimming laps in. The swimming workout itself was great – I had to share a lane for the first bit, but a lane freed up and I got in 80 laps to make up for a missed workout yesterday. After the pool, I went to pick up a package and headed to Subway to grab a sandwich to-go for dinner.</p> <p>In the evening, I drafted some emails to go out to professors and opened up my new monitor – all in all, definitely quite an eventful day! Glad to get through it with a stomach that feels good, for sure.</p> <h4 id="day-48-july-22nd-1"><u>Day 48 (July 22nd)</u></h4> <p>End of Week 7: Trip to Great Falls</p> <p>I woke up early today (7:30 AM) for a group REU to Great Falls, a nearby hiking trail with a waterfall. I left with the first group (AG, SK, JS, and AF), and we played some Alphabet Games and Contact! on the way to get the conversations flowing on the way there. We met up with ZS, SS, and LH, and proceeded to look at the waterfalls/hike for about two to three hours. On the way back, we stopped at Silver Diner, a really nice diner spot, for lunch. I switched cars along the way, heading back with ZS, SS, and LH, and when I made it back, I went straight to the UMD pool to get some laps in.</p> <p>After showering up after a workout, I proceeded to head out with ZS and SS for Qu Ramen, which was quite good. We stopped for some Kung Fu Tea before heading back, where I worked on some CodeForces and drafted some more emails. All in all, it was quite an eventful day and a great close to the seventh week of the REU! It was a lot of fun to interact with more of the REU on the hike &amp; lunch, and I hope to continue to do that with the remaining three weeks.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="caar"/><category term="research"/><category term="cs"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Week 7 of my Summer 2023 experience @ REU-CAAR.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">REU-CAAR, Week 6</title><link href="https://dyang5.github.io/blog/2023/REUCAAR-week6/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="REU-CAAR, Week 6"/><published>2023-07-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://dyang5.github.io/blog/2023/REUCAAR-week6</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://dyang5.github.io/blog/2023/REUCAAR-week6/"><![CDATA[<h4 id="day-36-july-10th"><u>Day 36 (July 10th)</u></h4> <p>Week 6, Day 1</p> <ul> <li> <p>8:30 - 9:00 AM: Week 6 here we go! Unfortunately, lane lines were being moved at the pool (again) and so my morning workout started closer to 8:40/8:45 than 8:30. Regardless, I managed to make the most out of the situation by going for 40 laps in just around 20 minutes, which is a much quicker pace (close to 2:00/100yd) than I have been going.</p> </li> <li> <p>10:00 AM - 12:00 PM: To start off this week, I wanted to wrap up my work with the confusion matrices that I’ve been coding (the confusion matrices show us which genders/races our classifier outputs compared to the true genders/races for all our images). Over the weekend, I was able to get the confusion matrices to show percentages, but I also wanted to show the raw numbers (in terms of how many examples it classified for each of the given predicted/true race and gender combos). In the morning, I managed to get the code working for our smaller testset example. As I’ve been doing throughout the last week, I always code up a sample, get it working on the testset, and then replicate the code for the entire FairFace validation set.</p> </li> <li> <p>12:00 - 1:00 PM: We had our weekly REU lunch talk. This time, Jim Purtilo, a Professor at UMD, talked about Software Engineering (what is it, what is important to succeed, etc.) and we got free catering from Q-Doba (note: important to get there early to make sure food does not run out). Overall, I thought it was a fun, interactive talk – and the ideals stressed to succeed in Software Engineering obviously apply to research as well (effective communication)!</p> </li> <li> <p>1:00 - 4:00 PM: The afternoon session was a bit less productive for me. I ran my updated confusion matrix code on my FairFace validation program, which takes a while. I’ve currently set it up so that the classifier results are saved in a CSV (so I can theoretically read the CSV for the results and save the time that the classifier takes to run on each of the 10,000 images in the FairFace validation set), but for now, I’ve just been running the classifier on the same set of images. I think this will change (the code to read the CSV is not terribly difficult) as I continue to run more tests, but since my work today essentially closed the chapter (for now) of testing the DeepFace classifier on the FairFace dataset, I will hold off on that front. Tomorrow, I’m hoping to start researching/looking into how I can implement the Linear Head approach I’ve been discussing throughout these notes. When I get the time, I’ll also happily share the confusion matrices I generated (essentially the product of my last week and a half which is cool yet a bit sad as I think I could have done it faster) here.</p> </li> </ul> <p>After research, PM and MA finally decided to purchase gym passes (their timing lines up with the start of the second summer session at the gym, meaning they pay less than what most of us paid at the start of the program – when it was the middle of the first summer session), so PM, MA, DS, SS, and I went to play basketball. SS wanted to get a healthier dinner (than CFA), so DS and I decided to join her at Yahentimisi, one of the main dining halls on campus, where we ran into CK. Afterwards, I went back to the dorm to relax, work on some CodeForces, and read. I’m starting the book “Atomic Habits,” which my parents brought over per my request when they came to visit. I think it’ll be good to get some reading in as it will mean less screentime before bed and more learning.</p> <h4 id="day-37-july-11th"><u>Day 37 (July 11th)</u></h4> <p>Week 6, Day 2</p> <ul> <li> <p>8:30 - 9:00 AM: Got my morning swim in today, going for 50 laps in just under 30 minutes. My arms and legs felt like jelly after playing basketball and swimming yesterday, but it was good to power through this morning.</p> </li> <li> <p>10:00 AM - 12:00 PM: I was hoping to start working on the linear head approach today. I started working on a related topic (one that we need to have working before we can even train a linear head) by combining my work over the last week with our previous “detect and classify program.” More specifically, we need to set up an image to classification pipeline which we will need to train a linear head. After running into some small errors, I took a break and joined the GatherTown (online environment where the virtual conference is held) for the <a href="https://virtual2023.aclweb.org/index.html">ACL: Association for Computational Linguistics Conference</a>, a conference that SS was planning to attend but cannot due to a visa situation. It turns out that another one of my friends who is a PhD student at UPenn is actually there in person as well, which is a cool coincidence. For some reason, the GatherTown is publically available, meaning I can interact with virtual participants/look at their posters; this was a nice “break” from research and it was definitely cool to look at all the work being done at this NLP conference.</p> </li> <li> <p>1:15 - 4:00 PM: I have to start by admitting that these last few afternoon sessions have not felt as productive as normal for me. After finishing up the image to classification pipeline that I had started in the morning (it was not too hard to fix this up), I mostly spent some time looking into how we can get Stable Diffusion (or really any other diffusion model) to run locally. The general pipeline we will need is Text-to-Image into Image-to-Classification into updating a Linear Head. Since we’ve solidified the first pipeline, we will need to work with the first one (Text-to-Image, essentially a diffusion model) before we start building out the third one.</p> </li> </ul> <p>After research, I took a nap (my first one of the REU) before grabbing some CFA for dinner. There were plans to watch a movie earlier (but still after research) but nothing materialized, but after waking up from my nap, I tried to get something going. I ended up watching “Taken” with the typical group (SS, DS, and AB). Tomorrow night, we’ll have a meeting with our advisor to update her on progress and to talk about next steps – I think this will be really useful as I orient myself for the second half of the REU.</p> <p>#### <u>Day 38 (July 12th)</u></p> <p>Week 6, Day 3 – Meeting Day #5</p> <ul> <li> <p>8:30 - 9:00 AM: Got to the pool at around the right time today and got in a solid workout – 50+ laps in just around 30 minutes. I’ve been feeling a bit out of it this week but it’s been good to push through and stay consistent with the swimming workouts.</p> </li> <li> <p>10:00 AM - 12:00 PM: As I wrote yesterday, my goal for now is to get Stable Diffusion (or really any diffusion model) working locally, so that I can start to generate images, pass it to the image-to-classifier pipeline, and then start to train a linear head on these results. After finding some tutorials on <a href="https://huggingface.co/blog/stable_diffusion">Stable Diffusion rom HuggingFace</a> and others, I began with some starter code and attempted to get it working. First, I copied over the work I’ve done to a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">nexus-scratch</code> local directory (that has 200 GB of memory compared to the 20 GB on our personal accounts), so that I can generate images with Stable Diffusion (which takes quite a bit of space). Unfortunately, this led to a debugging spiral – running the Stable Diffusion model in the scratch directory somehow used my local disk space (which there is not enough of) rather than the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">nexus-scratch</code> space that I have an abundance of. Heading into lunch, I was definitely frustrated as a number of attempts I had to fix the issue did not work.</p> </li> <li> <p>1:00 - 4:00 PM: After asking AF and XG for some suggestions on how to fix the storage issue, I followed some ideas given by AF (and StackExchange), finally fixing the issue. It turns out that I had to set three different shell environment variables to move my cache directory from my personal to my local <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">nexus-scratch</code> directory. Finally, after some long and frustrating debugging, my issue had been fixed. In the remaining time, I experimented with negative prompts to try and get the diffusion generated images (especially the faces on people) to be less deformed/blurry. I will continue to work on this tomorrow and start to extend this towards the linear head idea.</p> </li> </ul> <p>I’ve been feeling quite tired after research these last few days. I think part of this may be because I am a bit bummed about not having that much research progress, but I may also have to sleep earlier/swim less or not as intensively. I’m hoping this is just a bit of a rut I’m in but will continue to evaluate and prioritize my well-being.</p> <ul> <li>8:00 - 9:00 PM: Our group had originally planned to meet up in the basement and join the meeting, but plans fell through and we all ended up Zooming in from individual rooms. Our advisor showed up a bit late so we started closer to 8:10. I mainly discussed the DeepFace classifier results I had on the FairFace validation set and upcoming plans for the Linear Head approach. SS discussed her Erasing Concepts approach, AF her Domain Translator approach, and XG his Reinforcement Learning approach. Overall, I think we all have some work to do on our approaches – our advisor offered some suggestions but we all need to build on our approaches and experiment some more.</li> </ul> <h4 id="day-39-july-13th"><u>Day 39 (July 13th)</u></h4> <p>Week 6, Day 4</p> <ul> <li> <p>8:30 - 9:00 AM: I decided to skip my typical morning swim as I’ve been feeling a bit tired during morning workouts/in general this week. My plan was to go for a swim after a REU-planned talk (so after 5 PM – more on this later). I actually didn’t end up getting any extra sleep in since I set my normal alarms to see if I would feel okay about going out for a swim, but I did head over to Vigilante Coffee to grab some breakfast before the work day.</p> </li> <li> <p>10:00 AM - 12:00 PM: Just like I always do on Thursday mornings, I started off the day by attending my advisor’s graduate student meetings. Today, there was a talk about Diverse Reinforcement Learning that was pretty theory-heavy but still good to listen to. The meeting went short since there was only one presenter, leaving me some more time to work on the Stable Diffusion pipeline. I was running into the same problems as yesterday with the cache (for some reason, it seems like I have to run the commands I did every time I start up the server). To fix this, I added the commands to my <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">~/.bashrc</code> files and started to test some more. My goal over these next few days will be to improve the Stable Diffusion outputs on group images. I started working with some negative prompting (and it seemed to work relatively well yesterday), but after further testing today, the faces are still relatively deformed/blurry. Obviously, we want our generated images to be as good/high-quality as possible, so hopefully we can improve this a bit more.</p> </li> <li> <p>1:30 - 4:00 PM: My group ran into some problems with card access on Conference Rooms so we ended up working in a general working area. Any work progress, however, got quickly derailed by the news that someone in my dorm suite had tested positive for COVID, making me and others (including my other suitemates and their research groups) at risk. We were called down to take COVID tests (we all tested negative) and later told to isolate until Monday. For now, I feel okay and this seems to be more of an incovenience than a serious problem (the best case is that this is all it is), but it means that I will be working “from home” tomorrow and isolating in my room.</p> </li> <li> <p>4:00 - 5:00 PM: There was a research talk by Evan Golub on “How to Do Bad Science” that I was looking forward to (we were told to watch a TED talk and read some comics in preparation for the talk and ensuing discussion, and both of these were interesting), but obviously with the COVID situation, I had to miss out on the talk.</p> </li> </ul> <p>Post-research plans to go get my swimming workout in were obviously also derailed, but I did end up going for a quick 2-mile run before grabbing CFA dinner for the third day in a row (I was wearing a mask for this). For the rest of the week, I’ll be isolating and grabbing food with a mask on while working from home. This is a bit of a bummer but I’m hoping my REU friend recovers quickly and that no one else has COVID/becomes symptomatic. Fingers crossed!</p> <h4 id="day-40-july-14th"><u>Day 40 (July 14th)</u></h4> <p>Week 6, Day 5 – Work from Home Day 1</p> <ul> <li>10:00 AM - 12:00 PM: Since I’m self-isolating, I am not able to go for morning swims – instead, I get an extra hour of sleep. Today is the first and hopefully last day of working from home. I started the day by continuing my work from previous days – trying to get better diffusion model output for group pictures. For some reason, I was getting the same out of storage issues as I’ve been getting the past few days, and my <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.bashrc</code> file was completely empty! I quickly added the commands from before into the file and ran them in the terminal as well to set my cache to my scratch directory. It’s a bit annoying to have to deal with the same problems every time, but hopefully I won’t have to do this for much longer. After some basic experimentation with negative prompting and group images, I didn’t find any improvement in the stable diffusion generated images. For the remainder of the morning, I thought about some limitations of our project and added them to a slideshow for our next meeting. Some problems include:</li> </ul> <blockquote> <p>In our generative process, our stable diffusion generated images yield deformed/blurry faces for people in group photos. Obviously, we want the faces to be as normal/human-like as possible. (This is what I’ve been experimenting with the past few days, to not much progress). In our general pipeline, we use stable diffusion generated images (see above), then pass those generated images to a face detector/gender and race classifier. As I’ve written before, the gender/race classifier is itself imperfect/faulty (it especially has trouble separating Middle Eastern people from Latino Hispanic people). Since we are using this classifier in an attempt to get “fair image generation”, our “fair images” may also be affected…</p> </blockquote> <p>These are two big areas that we will need to further think about/address. We don’t have immediate answers for either of these yet either, but we will need to work on both of these areas (and others).</p> <ul> <li>1:00 - 4:00 PM: It turns out that the HVAC (water, air conditioning system) in Iribe, the main CS building where the rest of my group and other non-quarantined research groups are working, went out in the morning. From what I heard, everyone dispersed back to the Student Union for an early lunch, and my research group didn’t end up working together in the afternoon session. It sounds like it’s been a rough few days overall for the REU with the COVID positive case and the HVAC system going out. Overall, though, nothing really changed in my afternoon plans since I was working from home. I did a bit more experimentation with Stable Diffusion – it turns out that giving the prompt “give me a portrait photo of a doctor” (i.e. asking for a single person image output) along with negative prompts generates a much more realistic photo than the group image prompts. In the future, I’m hoping to test the classifier on the single-person generated images to get a sense of the problems we may have look more into.</li> </ul> <p>It has sucked not being able to do much outside of stay in my room due to the protocol for COVID isolation. Though I was planning to go for a run right before dinner, the minute I stepped outside, it started raining, which sucks. I went back to grab my umbrella and head over to grab some dinner from the Ramen shop nearby. On the way back, I also noticed that my umbrella is kind of broken, which double sucks. After letting my dinner digest for a bit, I went out for a three mile run around campus; it was a lot cooler than previous days, especially later at night, so the run felt quite nice. It’s definitely felt good to get a bit of exercise after staying in my room all day.</p> <h4 id="day-41-july-15th"><u>Day 41 (July 15th)</u></h4> <p>Week 6 Day 6</p> <p>Today was definitely a more chill day for me. In the morning, I worked on some CodeForces problems. For an early lunch, I finally finished the tub of Greek Yogurt I got a week or two ago (along with the Frozen Strawberries, Granola, etc). In the afternoon, I ended up going for a run to get in some exercise. I went on the Paint Branch Trail before running around a really nice lake (Lake Artemesia), where there are 1.3 mile loops around the lake. The run ended up being 3 miles (I had planned to run longer but was really tired), and I walked another loop around the lake before heading over to Playa Bowls to get some water and an acai bowl. I usually run later in the day (closer to dinner) but the weather report said it was going to thunder at 4 PM – it did not. Today was definitely a pretty basic yet relaxing Saturday; I’m feeling good health-wise as well and don’t appear to have any COVID-like symptoms.</p> <h4 id="day-42-july-16th"><u>Day 42 (July 16th)</u></h4> <p>The End of Week 6</p> <p>I woke up earlier today hoping to head out to grab some breakfast and then participate in the CodeForces contest. I’d say I kind of did both of these things – I heated up some Bagel Bites before the contest and ended up doing the problems concurrently (but not submitting anything since both the first two problems were tedious/long/tricky). I keep telling myself that I should be actually participating and submitting in these contests but honestly, both problems took me a while to solve. I am happy that at least I made the effort to participate in the contest/try the problems despite the fact that self-isolating has sort of sucked mentally (not meeting others, staying in the room, no swimming exercise).</p> <p>Post contest, I ended up submitting and debugging my work for B and reading a bit about a simple solution for A (some people said A was harder than C or D), which was a tough problem to get if you hadn’t seen it before. I also watched the Wimbledon Tennis finals, which was cool and motivating for me to play more tennis (unfortunately, not today even though I typically swim -&gt; tennis on Sundays since I’m supposed to be isolating for at least another day).</p> <p>In the afternoon, I mainly read and relaxed since all the screen time from the morning hurt my eyes. I went for a quick run around campus and then to Potomac Pizza, where I beasted 5 pieces of a Large Combo pizza down (I am realizing now that I had pizza-like food for both “meals” today). After a long, tiring walk back home (I was so full), I ended up cutting and eating up some of the watermelon my parents brought over.</p> <p>This was a good day to wrap up the sixth week. The only sad part of the day was that the monitor I ordered on Amazon for Prime Day seemed to not get delivered despite two attempts (all other Amazon packages I’ve ordered here have come perfectly fine), but it’ll hopefully arrive tomorrow. In terms of research, I’m back to some serious work tomorrow – I think I will work more on diffusion model output and analyze the results on the DeepFace classifier.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="caar"/><category term="research"/><category term="cs"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Week 6 of my Summer 2023 experience @ REU-CAAR.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">REU-CAAR, Week 5</title><link href="https://dyang5.github.io/blog/2023/REUCAAR-week5/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="REU-CAAR, Week 5"/><published>2023-07-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://dyang5.github.io/blog/2023/REUCAAR-week5</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://dyang5.github.io/blog/2023/REUCAAR-week5/"><![CDATA[<h4 id="day-29-july-3rd"><u>Day 29 (July 3rd)</u></h4> <p>Week 5, Day 1</p> <p>This is now the 5th week of the program, which is crazy to think! Today, we have an unofficial day off from the REU and my parents came to visit which was fun. After waking up later than normal, I went for a morning 50-lap swim. For lunch, I met up with my parents and we went to a Steakhouse, which was quite filling. After showing them my dorm, I split off and tried to get some research done.</p> <p>The most frustrating part is that the code I’ve written on my Jupyter Notebook still does not run using a GPU – even after my group gave me some suggestions and it looked like it might finally work, it just still doesn’t. I asked my advisor about this but it looks like I may have to move on for the time being and prepare for the presentation instead from tomorrow onwards. This really sucks because I spent about a week writing the code but now I don’t even get a chance to run it. I hope a workaround/fix will come soon.</p> <p>For dinner, AB, LH, ML, SS, ZS, SK, and two other non REU-CAAR students went to “Board ‘n Brew” to celebrate a birthday (not saying who for privacy concerns). We played some board games (the place is known for board games and food) and had a fun time with a large group which is always nice. Tomorrow is the 4th of July; I don’t have any crazy plans but will probably get both meals with my parents who are in town for a few more days. Other than that, I will hopefully have a lot of the presentation done/a fix to my Jupyter problem, but the latter seems relatively unlikely.</p> <h4 id="day-30-july-4th"><u>Day 30 (July 4th)</u></h4> <p>Week 5, Day 2</p> <p>Another day off – this time due to the 4th of July! After another 50 lap morning swim (the pools were packed today due to Masters Swimmers and families celebrating the 4th of July… I guess), I met up again with my parents. We went to a seafood restaurant for lunch before heading back to their hotel to get some work done. I talked to them a bunch about grad school applications, my research project and the challenges/next steps (also showing them some of our group’s presentations), and got a CodeForces problem done all in a few hours time. It was definitely good to catch up and to share what I’ve been working on and thinking about. I started working a bit more on the presentation we’re scheduled to have on July 6th. I’m still pretty bummed about the GPU problem and my code not running but that will have to wait – we may have a group meeting with our advisor tomorrow night (pending her reply) and we will certainly have to present Thursday morning, so these tasks take precedence.</p> <p>For dinner, my parents and I went to “China Buffet” (it turns out finding a restaurant open on July 4th is quite difficult), which was better than expected. Afterwards, I got dropped back off at my dorms. My parents are staying a night or two more before going to visit my brother at his camp on the East Coast, so they will be doing plenty of traveling these next few days.</p> <p>Despite potential Fireworks and S’mores plans being floated around by AG (our grad program leader), both plans ended up fizzling out (though we may do S’mores another time next week). I had a chill 4-day weekend but it’ll definitely be a busy day at research tomorrow with the presentation/meeting prep.</p> <h4 id="day-31-july-5th"><u>Day 31 (July 5th)</u></h4> <p>Week 5 Day 3: Meeting Day?</p> <ul> <li> <p>8:30 - 9:00 AM: First day back from a four day weekend; I had to start it off with my typical morning swim. I really didn’t feel like going today but my goal is to stay consistent with exercise and I did just that. Got 40 laps in at a relatively quick pace which was good as well. I was definitely shaking off some of that morning rust caused by our long 4-day weekend.</p> </li> <li> <p>10:00 AM - 12:30 PM: My main goal for today was to prep for the meeting (scheduled for later tonight) and presentation (scheduled for tmrw morning) and to present our work/motivation coherently and efficiently. I spent the morning for one last attempt to get TensorFlow working with the Cluster’s CPUs, once again to no avail. As a result, I decided it would just be better to wait out the 1-2 hour runtime and run the program locally using the CPU. After staying an extra thirty minutes in hopes that the program would finish, I left the program running in the room with the help of Caffeine and just hoped that nobody would take my computer (it is pretty safe since you have to scan into the room to get in).</p> </li> <li> <p>1:15 - 4:00 PM: After lunch, the REU congregated in our main room for some free ice cream and math problems given by Bill. For the interested, they include “using two colors to color the cells of a 3x9 (3x8, 3x7, and later 3x6 as extensions), prove or disprove the fact that there will always be a rectangle with monochromatic endpoints.”</p> </li> </ul> <p>After the ice cream session, we went back to our research room to get some work done. I found out that the program I had been running broke due to an error on the line after the classifier, meaning had to run it all again. This was a bummer but another run and another hour and a half later, I had some results for the DeepFace classifier on the FairFace validation set. The gender accuracy was 65% and the race accuracy was 60.8%, which isn’t as good as I would have hoped for. In comparison to XG’s EfficientNetV2 model trained on FairFace’s train (95% gender accuracy, 70% race), these accuracies aren’t good either. However, it is important to note that the DeepFace classifier is not trained on FairFace, and may perform better when we use it in combination with YOLOv8 on diffusion-generated images. For now, I think I’ll move on from the classifier and try to build on a differnt idea (the “linear head” approach – we want to add the linear head we train using gradient descent and some loss functions to the text encoder and we think this process may lead to more fair image generation).</p> <ul> <li>8:00 - 9:00 PM: Our meeting was supposed to be during this time, but our advisor is feeling really sick and could not make it. In this regard, I think our presentation tomorrow will be a bit more important (she will probably make it to this one) as it will serve both as an update to our advisor as well as a general invitation to the grad group for any interested students/suggestions to improve our project.</li> </ul> <p>After research, I had mainly relaxed in preparation for our anticipated group meeting. After finding out that the meeting had been canceled, per my advisor’s requests, I left an update to the Slack channel to the work I did this week. I also watched Suicide Squad along with SS, AB, and DS, before calling it a night. Hoping the meeting tomorrow goes well – looking at it now, my parts are complete so I’m hoping my group finishes up and we have a sucessful presentation tomorrow.</p> <h4 id="day-32-july-6th"><u>Day 32 (July 6th)</u></h4> <p>Week 5 Day 4: Group Grad Meeting</p> <ul> <li> <p>8:30 - 9:00 AM: Morning swim. Meant to get out early today because of the important group meeting later at 10, and I did. I got in 50 laps in just around 30 minutes, which is quite quick compared to my other efforts.</p> </li> <li> <p>10:00 AM - 12:00 PM: Today was our all important group meeting with our advisor and her graduate students. After some early time concerns (we got pushed to start the meeting since the first planned speaker’s microphone was not working, and SS somehow snoozed her 3 alarms for the first time in a few weeks and had to Zoom in for the presentation), we quickly got started. We went over some of our motivation/project goals, before diving into our methodology and the experiments we’ve worked on thus far, and concluding with future work and exploration. Overall, the reception to our presentation seemed positive, and our advisor (as well as a few graduate students) gave us a few important suggestions/points to think about, including reconsidering one of our fairness notions. In our approach, we consider “fairness loss” (which aims to get the confidence each person in an image is male to be near 0.5) and “confidence loss” (which aims to get each person distinctly male or female). An important point that was brought up is that in a picture of a hospital context, there could be 10 people, 5 doctors and 5 nurses. With our current fairness notion, if all 5 doctors were male and all 5 nurses were female, the general proportion would be 50-50 resulting in a “fair image,” but our approach does not account for the fact that the gender among occupation groups is not fair at all. This is an important fact/scenario we will have to account for, and we had some discussions about how we can do so (we may combine our approach with another that “erases biased concepts from diffusion models”). Overall, it was quite nice to hear some feedback about the presentation and to more formally present it in front of a bigger audience. Our presentation was followed by another on Source Free Domain Adaptation (notes to be completed later).</p> </li> <li> <p>1:00 - 3:00 PM: In the afternoon session, I spent most of my time decompressing from the (relatively) stressful/important morning meeting as well as trying to understand the work done in the aforementioned <a href="Erasing Concepts from Diffusion Models">https://arxiv.org/pdf/2303.07345.pdf</a> paper, which SS is working on implementing/experimenting with. This paper may come up useful in combination with our other work, so I am hoping to finish thoroughly reading it tomorrow and to begin working on a new angle to our project.</p> </li> <li> <p>3:00 - 4:00 PM: We had a talk by Associate Professor at UMD Dana Dachman-Soled on “Types of Cyber Security Attacks.” The talk was explained at a high level which made it easier to follow than some of our previous talks, and so it was quite interesting overall. A goal of mine is to attend every talk in this program (and I’ve been on track thus far) – lately, a lot of people have been skipping these talks but I personally think it’s important to hear from different speakers in different areas to get a better sense of the work being done as well as hopefully learn some new things.</p> </li> <li> <p>4:30 - 9:00 PM: Today was a Board Game Night! hosted by Bill for the REU. A number of people came, including SS, AZ, LH, ML, MA, PM, DS, SK, ZS, CL, XG, and AB (at least 2/3 of the program). We got free pizza and I played a bunch of board games, including but not limited to SET!, Dixit, Texas Hold ‘Em, and Just One (a word guessing game). We also got free pizza from Potomac which was pretty nice. I noticed that I am a bit particular about how games are played (I prefer them to be a bit more orderly) and I got a few comments from others about that, but overall it was a fun time, and it was great that the REU organized this event.</p> </li> </ul> <p>This was an important but short day for research but a quite fun day overall.</p> <h4 id="day-33-july-7th"><u>Day 33 (July 7th)</u></h4> <p>Week 5 Day 5: The Halfway Point</p> <ul> <li> <p>8:30 - 9:00 AM: Short morning swim today; I ended up going for just around 25 laps in 15ish minutes. The lane lines were being shuffled again and so I spent the first 15 minutes of my usual swim time waiting out on the deck, which sucked a bit. There was one person who just swam through it which was a bit weird/seemed disrespectful but the lifeguards didn’t seem to mind too much – maybe I should’ve done that?</p> </li> <li> <p>10:00 AM - 12:00 PM: I started the morning by finishing up the “Erasing Concepts from Diffusion Models” paper from yesterday. I think if we are to apply the strategy from that paper, we will need to be really careful that erasing a concept does not alter images with other concepts too drastically, which is an issue that the paper mentioned (especially since we are dealing with a larger, much more prevalent “concept/idea” in gender rather than a given artist style or nudity like in the paper). Instead of completely starting a new approach today, I decided to formalize some of the analysis I had done with the DeepFace classifier on our basic test set so we can more carefully analyze the results on the FairFace validation set.</p> </li> <li> <p>1:00 - 4:00 PM: Continuing from my work in the morning, I started working on a framework that compares the true gender and race labels to the predicted ones as well relative confidence our classifier gave given the true gender and race, and visualizing these results with confusion matrices. In doing so, we can more carefully analyze the types of mistakes the classifier makes and when it makes them. This went pretty well – I was able to get the confusion matrices working on the test set and plan to run the equivalent code to generate the confusion matrices for both the labels and the confidences of the classifier on the FairFace validation set (where it had the 65% ish gender and 60% race accuracy). This will be a good segue into the second half of the REU where I hope to build on one of the main approaches (linear head, domain translator, reinforcement learning, or even erasing concepts) we were planning on implementing for fair images.</p> </li> </ul> <p>For dinner, AB, SS, MA, and I went to Taqueria Habanero, a nearby Mexican food spot, which was quite good. The portion size for my tacos seemed small at first, but I think it filled me up (and the free tortilla chips were great). After grabbing some sort of boba dessert from a nearby Boba place, we headed back to the dorms and I played some Super Smash Bros with MA, NL, PM, and AB. I would have rather done some CodeForces (I did this later) but I wanted to socialize a bit more with some of the other REU students. Tomorrow, I’m hoping to relax a bit, get in a long swim, and get some more work done with CodeForces and maybe some research/grad school planning/reading.</p> <p>It’s crazy to think we are essentially halfway through the REU now, but I’ve been happy with how everything has gone socially, physically, and academically thus far.</p> <h4 id="day-34-july-8th"><u>Day 34 (July 8th)</u></h4> <p>Week 5 Day 6</p> <p>Woke up today and went out for a Saturday long swim – I ended up swimming for 50 minutes, going for 80 laps and 2000+ yards, which felt great. I somehow swam a 1:10 100 free for the final four laps of the workout, which is awesome. Strength wise, I haven’t done a swim of over 35 minutes since I’ve been here (and this one was about 15 minutes longer than that), but I hope to keep building on this (and maybe do 100 laps at the end of the program).</p> <p>After swimming, I went back to make some Parfait-like concoction for lunch (Greek Yogurt, Frozen Strawberries, Granola, crushed butter waffles) before working on problems from the most recent CodeForces contest (1846). For dinner, I went on my own to grab some Poke from “The Spot Mini” which was yummy. Definitely a nice, chill individual day highlighted by a solid morning workout.</p> <h4 id="day-35-july-9th"><u>Day 35 (July 9th)</u></h4> <p>The True Halfway Point: The End of Week Five</p> <p>On the weekends I wake up a little later than I would like to. Since the pool opens at 10 AM on Sundays and I typically play tennis at 11, I have this dichotomy between swimming before or after tennis (after would make more sense because it is usually quite hot out and a dip in the pool feels quick nice). In most weekends, I’ve been swimming before tennis and I did the same this week.</p> <p>My morning swim was short and not quite as fun as normal – the lanes were all taken and the swimmers who had single lanes just kept swimming without even looking in my direction (I was going to ask if they were willing to share the lane), which was sad. This meant I swam in the deep end, where laps are around half the distance, for the first 15ish minutes. Luckily, I was later able to grab a lane and swam there for a bit until it was time to leave for tennis. I played tennis with AF and SS before getting some Playa Bowls for lunch.</p> <p>In the afternoon, I mostly lounged around before heading out for a walk at 2ish. After a bit, it got really windy out and thunderstorm-like, so I went back to run some code for research and work on some CodeForces. In the evening, I grabbed some Ramen on my own (it seemed like nobody else was really interested in going out this weekend) from Onikama Ramen Bar before retiring to my room for more CodeForces and other activities. Again, a nice chill day to round out the first half of the REU.</p> <p>To copy my summary from a few days ago, “it’s crazy to think we are essentially halfway through the REU now, but I’ve been happy with how everything has gone socially, physically, and academically thus far.” I hope the second half is even more fruitful in these regards and that I can build on this positive momentum from the first half!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="caar"/><category term="research"/><category term="cs"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Week 5 of my Summer 2023 experience @ REU-CAAR.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">REU-CAAR, Week 4</title><link href="https://dyang5.github.io/blog/2023/REUCAAR-week4/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="REU-CAAR, Week 4"/><published>2023-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://dyang5.github.io/blog/2023/REUCAAR-week4</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://dyang5.github.io/blog/2023/REUCAAR-week4/"><![CDATA[<h4 id="day-22-june-26th"><u>Day 22 (June 26th)</u></h4> <p>Week 4, Day 1</p> <p>I can’t believe we’re already on the 4th week of this program…</p> <ul> <li> <p>8:30 - 9:00 AM: Got out earlier than normal for my morning swim, but the lifeguards were doing some lane-line moving due to a swim group coming in before me. Unlike the previous lane-line shift, these lifeguards kept me out of the pool, and so I only got in 18ish minutes of a swim this morning. I was definitely a bit bummed about that but I can understand that the lifeguards are just trying to do their job.</p> </li> <li> <p>10:00 - 11:30 AM: Shorter morning session today due to an earlier lunch talk. SS and I spent the morning working on incorporating our test set and modifying our program to run on a folder of images (mainly SS). Otherwise, I worked on a presentation for our meeting tomorrow night with our advisor, which summarizes the work we’ve been doing and questions we have.</p> </li> <li> <p>11:30 AM - 12:45 PM: Daniel Apon, an Adjunct Professor of CS here who has done industry work in Post-Quantum Crytography, came in for a lunch talk today and talked about his career path, along with what he did in each of his roles at NIST (National Institute of Standards and Technology) and MITRE. I thought the talk was quite good – there was not much heavy theory but he explained the work he did/related concepts quite clearly. I find that many of these invited speakers are quite charismatic while being brilliant, and that’s really cool to see. It was cool to also learn a bit more about Cryptography and his work, which was on the Applied Pure Math side – something I might be interested in doing in my career as well.</p> </li> <li> <p>1:00 - 4:00 PM: After modifying our testing program to run on a “test set” of images, we manually classified the genders for each person in our dataset. It turns out that SS’s face detection &amp; gender classification model has a 53% accuracy whereas my object detection &amp; gender classification model has a 47% accuracy. These are obviously quite poor – by straight up guessing, we might expect a 50% accuracy. We’ll definitely need to present these results to our advisor and talk about potential fixes – or test a separate gender classification model (or maybe even train our own). I’m not terribly worried about these numbers just yet since we are sort of just experimenting (and using pretrained models), but if the issues persist after a week or two, this could be cause for concern. Another small concern is that the detection model we are using, YOLOv8, is very well-known and widely-used, but it seems like the creators of the model have not cared to write a paper about it or the architecture they use; this seems a bit weird considering their whole goal is to be open-source and advance AI detection models. We’ll also need to ask our advisor about that. Near the end of the research day, I picked up a check from the REU for the first two-three weeks, which was nice.</p> </li> <li> <p>5:00 - 6:00 PM: Second swim of the day. Really nice effort (31 laps in just around 20 minutes). I might do more of these doubles if I feel good/it makes sense weather-wise, because more exercise is always welcome (and fun).</p> </li> </ul> <p>Post-research, I had planned to go play tennis with NL and MA, but it was nearly 90 degrees out and way too hot for that. Consequently, I decided to go for another pool swim, which fit the weather much better. For some reason, I felt motivated to do some “sets” (short but speedy mini-workouts) and was quite pleased to notice my general endurance/effort. Maybe all the exercise is paying off; I definitely feel good about where I’m at, but the swimming efforts show it too. I think this is definitely one + about a REU compared to research at a home institution – at a LAC like Swarthmore, general resources are limited (athletic facilities, connection with other research students, etc.) whereas at a REU, all of these things are widely available. A bonus is the research of course, which hopefully will continue to go smoothly and successfully. For any interested readers, I would definitely recommend applying to REUs ASAP.</p> <h4 id="day-23-june-27th"><u>Day 23 (June 27th)</u></h4> <p>Week 4, Day 2; Meeting Day 4</p> <ul> <li> <p>8:30 - 9:00 AM: Morning swim. Did two of the 4x50 workouts I mentioned in a previous entry, which was great. I ended up going for 27ish minutes and 40 laps, which I was happy with.</p> </li> <li> <p>10:00 AM - 12:00 PM: Since today is our presentation day, we spent much of the morning going through the presentation and our individual talking points. SS was out for the morning, and so I presented the existing presentation to AF and XG to hear their thoughts and to make sure that everyone had material to go over. After presenting the gender classifier results, XG wanted to try a different gender classifier model and went to experiment with EfficientNet, and to train it on a face dataset like FairFace. After further consideration, I realized that a gender classifier that has an accuracy of 50% is honestly quite bad – and I couldn’t figure out why the Caffe model, even though it is a bit outdated, was performing that badly. Consequently, I also went to look for different models to implement, and I found the <a href="https://github.com/serengil/deepface">DeepFace</a> classifier.</p> </li> <li> <p>1:00 - 4:00 PM: After taking some time to look through the DeepFace documentation and various tutorials, I spent the afternoon setting up DeepFace on my machine. Since I couldn’t figure out how to integrate the DeepFace face detection into my code, I stuck with the YOLOv8 face detection that my group has been working with for the last week (which is fine – the detection is good but the gender classifier was the main bottleneck in performance). Running the DeepFace analyzer to get the gender and race of the detected faces, I found a noticeable difference in performance – of the 11 images (roughly 50+ faces), the classifier gave a 85%-ish accuracy for both gender and race, which is a great improvement. We promptly added these results to our presentation and plan to continue working with the DeepFace classifier.</p> </li> </ul> <p>It was raining after research, so I went back to the dorms to relax before our meeting. I grabbed some CFA for dinner (and found out that I have around $860 dollars left for the remaining 6 and a half weeks). I then looked over the presentation a bit and walked through my parts.</p> <ul> <li>8:00 - 8:45 PM: Meeting time with our advisor. The meeting itself went relatively smoothly – this meeting was a bit different than others in the sense that we were presenting what we have been working on rather than sort of pitching our project ideas/discussing literature review. SS and I talked about the work we have been doing with YOLOv8 and the DeepFace classifier (as well as our previous Caffe gender classifier from <a href="https://talhassner.github.io/home/publication/2015_CVPR">Levi and Hassner</a>). AF and XG presented their work on domain translators and RL, and we all discussed next steps, which include testing the DeepFace classifier on a larger, labeled dataset and comparing the results to the EfficientNet approach XG is trying. The main tips we got were to make greater use of pre-existing work (with regards to models such as the gender classifier ones, RL approaches, and domain translators) and to ask more questions if we’re stuck in the group Slack channels. Our advisor also talked a bit about potentially splitting up work to prep for writing papers (she mentioned that it’s usually unheard of to have four co-authors on the same paper). I am not too worried about this but I imagine that we will have this conversation together as a group when the time comes; the positive side of this is that our advisor seems to think that we’ll have a paper out given our overall trend, which is great! I know that other REU participants have mentioned that their advisors are less than optimistic about paper chances and that they are bummed about that; maybe ML is just different in that sense, but who knows?</li> </ul> <p>Overall, it was definitely a “productive” and successful day for me due to the DeepFace classifier implementation.</p> <h4 id="day-24-june-28th"><u>Day 24 (June 28th)</u></h4> <p>Week 4, Day 3</p> <ul> <li> <p>8:30 - 9:00 AM: Morning swim! I went for the whole 30 minutes and swam for 45+ laps. I’m really happy with my consistency and general fitness progress this summer; hopefully I keep it up.</p> </li> <li> <p>10:00 AM - 12:00 PM: As I wrote yesterday, my main goal today was to test the DeepFace classifier on a large labeled face dataset like FairFace. In the morning, I spent most of my time trying to convert FairFace’s validation dataset labels and the corresponding csv file to match the output of the DeepFace classifier, using Python’s <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pandas</code> library (frequently used for data analysis). For example, I replaced instances of “Southeast Asian” and “East Asian” in the race label for the FairFace dataset to “asian” (since the DeepFace race classifier does not differentiate between Southeast and East Asians). In general, this process probably took longer than it should have but it was good to get some more experience using <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pandas</code> even if I could have done the process much quicker manually. (This process also reminded me of some of the work I did with my group in my ML final project at Swarthmore)</p> </li> <li> <p>1:00 - 4:00 PM: The next step of our work is to actually test the DeepFace gender and race classifiers on the FairFace dataset. To do this, I downloaded the FairFace validation set (with face images and their corresponding labels) and moved them onto the cluster (this took quite a while – I made the mistake of unzipping the validation folder before moving it to the cluster, which made the process slower). I also wrote skeleton code for testing the classifier using XG’s code that he used to train/validate the EfficientNet model he’s been working on. I don’t think this is fully complete and will need to go back to working on this tomorrow; I’m definitely hopeful that I’ll have analysis of the DeepFace classifier on the FairFace dataset by the end of the week.</p> </li> </ul> <p>I stayed a bit after research to make sure that all the FairFace files had been copied to the cluster. Afterwards, I headed back to the dorms to relax before going to the gym to play some basketball with DS, AB, and SS. It was definitely good to get some more exercise in (my first indoor exercise in a week and a half at least) and shoot some hoops – though I did end up getting some blisters because of my poor choice of socks. Afterwards, we grabbed some CFA before it closed at 7 PM, and I went back to do CodeForces and other related work.</p> <h4 id="day-25-june-29th"><u>Day 25 (June 29th)</u></h4> <p>Week 4, Day 4</p> <ul> <li> <p>8:30 - 9:00 AM: AQI went up to 120 in the morning (150 now), making the air “Unhealthy.” As a result, I made the decision to not swim in the morning, which kind of sucked but was probably better for overall health.</p> </li> <li> <p>10:00 AM - 12:00 PM: As is customary on Thursday mornings, I logged onto Zoom to join my advisor’s group research meetings. Today, a few grad students discussed their relative intern projects at Chevron (which was related to VLMs) and Capital One. Another student gave a research talk on “Hyper-Dimensional Function Encoding and its Extensions.” The first two talks had some confidential details, and so I refrained from note-taking. The other talk was more math-focused and a bit difficult to follow along note-wise, but the notes I took for that talk are available in the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Notes</code> folder as per usual.</p> </li> <li> <p>1:00 - 4:00 PM: As I’ve been working on for the last few days, I continued to try to set up my work in preparation for analysis on the FairFace dataset. To start, I initially chose to focus my analysis on the smaller testset with 10ish images and 50ish people. My reasoning for this is that I don’t want to have to run large jobs on the cluster over and over to get the analysis I want, and so I want to have a mini-example of all the analysis I want using the testset that I can simply reuse on the larger FairFace dataset. Since yesterday I managed to align the FairFace labels with the DeepFace classifier’s outputs, I spent most of today trying to further set up the analysis. The first problem was a small error in how we were saving the cropped image files – we were saving them as “[name].jpg_{number}.jpg” (notice the two <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.jpg</code>s), whereas the file names only contain the ending suffix. The main work I did today (which took nearly two hours to fix – the error was actually that a random <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.DS_Store</code> somehow got saved in our examples folder, making our program fail to crop images) was to standardize the file names. As explained above, the error itself was quite small and relatively simple, but it took a long time to debug since <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.DS_Store</code> files do not show in the directories unless you run <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">ls -a</code>. It was hilarious that this stalled me for so long but definitely a good learning experience.</p> </li> </ul> <p>In general, progress is a bit slower than I would like (I want to run the DeepFace classifier on FairFace by the end of the week), but all these steps are common steps in Machine Learning and it’s good that I’m getting to code through it, even if it is a tedious process. More progress (actually setting up to match outputs between classifier and hand-labeled testset data, which we also made today) to be made tomorrow, hopefully!</p> <ul> <li>4:00 - 5:00 PM: Listened to a talk by Professor Maria Cameron (Math REU director) on “Quantifying Rare Events in Stochastic Systems.” Even with previous Applied Math experience, the talk was a bit hard to follow, but it’s always good to hear about what others are working on.</li> </ul> <p>After research, I grabbed some Union Pizza for dinner (after also having it for the first time for lunch) since I wanted to stay away from having CFA for back to back dinners. I ended up in NL’s suite with LH, SK, and DS, where we talked over dinner and more afterwards.</p> <h4 id="day-26-june-30th"><u>Day 26 (June 30th)</u></h4> <p>Week 4, Day 5</p> <ul> <li> <p>8:30 - 9:00 AM: Since the AQI was at 150ish yesterday, I didn’t have much hope for a morning swim. When I woke up, it was around 120 which is still Unhealthy for Sensitive Groups, so no swim for me today.</p> </li> <li> <p>10:00 AM - 12:00 PM: My job was to continue with my work from the previous days. It sucks that progress isn’t going as fast as how easy the task may seem, but as I said previously, I think it’s good for me to get this coding practice in. In the morning, I finished my “toy dataset”, finishing up analysis comparing the test set’s ground truth labels with the DeepFace classifier’s output. On the 50ish people in the dataset, it got nearly 90% of the genders correctly labeled and 70% of the races correctly labeled (though again, the “race labels” were hand-labeled and a combination of decisions made by our research group – so many of the races were ambiguous). Though I only compared the “dominant race” (i.e. the one that the classifier had the highest confidence for) outputs, it was good to see that for many of the examples it classified “incorrectly,” the classifier also had a relatively high confidence for the “ground-truth label.”</p> </li> <li> <p>1:00 - 4:00 PM: In the afternoon session, I wrote some smaller code to extend my work on the toy dataset to the actual FairFace validation set, so we can better analyze the DeepFace gender classifier and its errors on labeled, facial images. After taking some time to set up the code and also attending a PhD defense for Eleftheria Briakou (a grad mentor for the “Machine Translation for Wikipedia Group”) on her project “Detecting Fine-Grained Semantic Divergences to Improve Translation Understanding Across Languages,” I tried to run the code on the cluster – after a hour, my Jupyter Notebook bugged and there was no progress. After some brief reflection (and asking around), I realized that I should be running the Notebook on a GPU from the cluster, and so I spent the rest of the day trying to get that running. To put it simply, this did not work, as so even though I know what (preliminary) code I want to run, I haven’t been able to get it done using the FairFace validation set. I definitely want to try this a bit more over the long four-day weekend (due to the 4th of July and optional day on Monday) so that I can hopefully have some more detailed analysis to show for on either our next meeting with our advisor or our July 6th meeting.</p> </li> </ul> <p>I stayed a bit after research to try to figure how to use a GPU to run my code – without any avail. It somehow started raining out, so I waited out the rain before heading back to the dorms when it was raining a bit less. For dinner, I had some leftovers from my PE lunch and combined it with some older leftovers from QD. Afterwards, I watched “The Menu” with LH, SS, AB, MA (and CK briefly) before resting for the night.</p> <h4 id="day-27-july-1st"><u>Day 27 (July 1st)</u></h4> <p>Week 4, Day 6</p> <p>Today was the first day of a four day weekend for us. Luckily, the AQI was a lot better so I went for a 50 lap swim in the morning with SS. Despite learning that the Masters Swimmers swim from 8:45 - 10:30ish which caused a lot of the lanes to be filled up, the workout was really nice and it was good to get back in the pool after two days of no swimming.</p> <p>Afterwards, I grab some Panda Express for lunch and retired to my room to chill and work on some CodeForces problems. For dinner, I went to LaoTao Hotpot with AB, SS, LH, NL, SK, and a student from REU-MATH; this was my first hotpot experience outside of having it with my family and it was pretty good. Overall, a nice and chill day.</p> <h4 id="day-28-july-2nd-"><u>Day 28 (July 2nd) </u></h4> <p>Last Day of Week 4</p> <p>I woke up a bit later than normal and went for a quick morning swim (25 min, 40 laps) before a tennis session with NL. I spent the afternoon mostly lounging around and trying to get my code to run on the cluster’s GPU resources (to no avail, unfortunately). For dinner, I went with AB to Root’s Natural Kitchen, a healthier Q-Doba alternative that was better than I expected, and grabbed some basic food (Granola, Yogurt, Strawberries) from Trader Joe’s.</p> <p>And this concludes Week 4 of the REU! Time goes by so fast – I’m a bit bummed about how little comparatively I was able to get done in research this week but I’ve been taking baby steps towards the end goal, and I guess that’s alright. We have two days off to start the week (July 3rd and 4th) and my parents will be visiting, before a meeting and a presentation for our research group later in the week – so it will be a busy one.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="caar"/><category term="research"/><category term="cs"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Week 4 of my Summer 2023 experience @ REU-CAAR.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">REU-CAAR, Week 3</title><link href="https://dyang5.github.io/blog/2023/REUCAAR-week3/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="REU-CAAR, Week 3"/><published>2023-06-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://dyang5.github.io/blog/2023/REUCAAR-week3</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://dyang5.github.io/blog/2023/REUCAAR-week3/"><![CDATA[<h4 id="day-15-june-19th"><u>Day 15 (June 19th)</u></h4> <p>Week 3, Day 1</p> <ul> <li>Today was Juneteenth, so we had the day off. This helped me relax a bit more over the weekend, but I know there will be plenty to do tomorrow as well. I went for a typical morning swim – though I went near 10:00 today so there was a lot more people (including some Masters Swimmers). After a nice workout, I played some tennis with AF before grabbing a Ramen lunch with AF as well. Work wise, I spent most of the day working on Ranom Numbers (an 1800 rated CodeForces problem). This took me a few hours (the initial solution I came up with, that I was debugging for a quite a while, had a flaw in it and was incorrect). For dinner, SS, AF, DS, and I went to The Spot Mini, a nice Poke Bowl place nearby. I came back, did laundry, debugged my CodeForces problem some more, and finally got it. Despite having to look at the Editorial, this was a nice end to the extra rest day.</li> </ul> <p>Tomorrow, my research group will discuss what our next steps are and what we want to share with our advisor in a meeting on Wednesday.</p> <h4 id="day-16-june-20th"><u>Day 16 (June 20th)</u></h4> <p>Surprise Second Meeting Day</p> <ul> <li> <p>8:30 - 9:00 AM: Morning swim to mark the “official” start of the third week of REU-CAAR. Good 20 minute-ish workout – I still want to get out of bed a bit earlier to get this up to 25-30 minutes each day.</p> </li> <li> <p>10:00 AM - 12:00 PM: After finding out that our Wednesday meeting time we did last week was booked for this week, I had to set up a last-minute meeting change; my group decided that it would be best to meet tonight – making today our all-important prep day. In the morning, we focused on summarizing our work from the last week and formalizing the ideas we had been thinking about. This was a really productive morning; we were actually able to fine-tune one of our “group fairness” (trying to make the output of a diffusion model more “fair” in terms of gender balance) more clearly, and define differentiable loss functions (which are necessary for gradient descent/weight updating in neural networks).</p> </li> <li> <p>12:00 - 1:30 PM: We listened to a talk on “Chess Playing Computers” (the history of AI in Chess and the advances over time) by Clyde Kruskal, who is an Associate Professor of CS at UMD. Crazily enough, I learned that he is the nephew of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joseph_Kruskal">Joseph Kruskal</a>, who made the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kruskal%27s_algorithm">Kruskal MST Algorithm</a>. He discussed Monte Carlo Tree Search, Minimax, Alpha-Beta Pruning, and a number of other advances I had seen from my AI class at Swarthmore. I found it quite funny how energetic and quick-witted he was – just like Bill, these older professors have a fun and unique energy to them, which I definitely want to have if I get old in academia. Another cool fact is that his father was apparently the first person to play against an AI in chess, which is absolutely crazy.</p> </li> <li> <p>1:30 - 4:00 PM: My research group continued gathering our thoughts and prepping for our meeting with our advisor. After forming a Meeting Abstract and aggregating our work/notes, SS had the idea to make a presentation. Though my group reluctantly agreed, this was actually a great idea as it’s much easier to demonstrate our main idea through pictures rather than words. Also, given the remote (Zoom) format of our meetings, it definitely makes it easier for our advisor to follow along. We aggregated our thoughts and divided the slides into presentation points. I thought today was overall quite productive and it gave me good confidence heading into the meeting.</p> </li> </ul> <p>I was super tired after research so I took a quick nap afterwards. For dinner, I grabbed some CFA – there were so many people in STAMP today due to another session of New Student Orientation – before heading back to my dorm to look over my slides.</p> <ul> <li>8:00 - 9:00 PM: Research Meeting Time! Just like last week, AF, SS, and I Zoomed in from the basement while XG Zoomed from home. This time, to avoid all working on the same computer, we put in our Airpods and decided to make it so only one of us would remain unmuted at a time. Though there was a bit of an echo (since we heard each other in person before our Airpods would pick it up on Zoom), this turned out to be a great arrangement.</li> </ul> <blockquote> <p>Content wise, I think the meeting went really well. The presentation format allowed us to explain our ideas much more clearly. At first, our advisor was asking many questions regarding our approach, but all of them were important points and helped us think about how to generalize our approach (our notion of “fair representation” is mainly gender-based, how will we extend this to other demographic groups/sensitive attributes?); I think these questions also helped us explain our idea more clearly to her. After each of our slides, she would ask us a few questions and we would clarify/expand on our solutions. There is a lot of details here, so I will leave them out and add them as we make progress on our project. I was particularly happy about the reception to our loss function definitions (we want to both minimize what we call “fairness loss” – which attempts to mitigate the gender bias by getting the proportion of males generated to be as close to 0.5 as possible – and “confidence loss” – which forces images to be clearly male-defined or female-defined and not a “blob”/androgynous); she was excited that we had explained the mathematical reasoning behind our definitions. We actually just worked on this idea this morning, so it was great to see that come to fruition and be well-received. Overall, there are a bunch of avenues to explore code-wise (this will be difficult especially for me, but it’s good to have more to learn and work on), but it seems like our next steps will be to set up an “Experiment Plan” (determining what dataset(s) to use, what models to run, what scripts we will need, etc.). Our advisor wants to check in with us about this before we run anything, which is really great as well as she’ll be there to give us more guidance.</p> </blockquote> <p>Overall, today was great – meeting wise, the feedback seemed positive and we were really happy about that. We also have more direction; rather than trying to formulate more ideas, we have a few that we are hopefully able to build on and test out more!</p> <h4 id="day-17-june-21st"><u>Day 17 (June 21st)</u></h4> <p>Week 3, Day 3</p> <ul> <li> <p>8:30 AM - 9:00 AM: Went for my typical morning swim today. When I woke up tired at around 8 AM and the weather report said that it was raining outside (which it was), I decided to simply enjoy an extra hour of sleep and go back to bed. After I saw that it would essentially rain for the next week, I quickly convinced myself that I would have to exercise/swim in the morning rain, otherwise it would be hard to get any exercise in this entire week. For the most part, swimming in the rain is not bad at all – it’s just the walk back that is a bit rough. I will bring my umbrella for tomorrow’s workout.</p> </li> <li> <p>10:00 AM - 12:00 PM: In our morning research session, I typed up the notes I had scribbled down during our meeting with our advisor yesterday night, and we discussed the feedback we received as a group. XG was quick to point out potential complications with our main approach (training a linear head on an encoder after using a face detector/gender classifier with our own loss functions to train the head) – namely that after the derivative can be noisy after back-propagating through a large amount of layers (I may be explaining this part wrong). We talked through potential solutions but concluded that one of our other ideas (Reinforcement Learning with rewards) may work better. Since we were having a positive group discussion (and my previous attempts to convince my group had failed), I decided against going to listen to Bill’s Ramsey Theory talk – an optional talk (but one that the REU was invited to) that was meant for some of the high school students he’s working with. I was a bit bummed about that, as I later heard that the Comp Geometry group ended up attending.</p> </li> <li> <p>1:15 - 4:00 PM: The afternoon session continued with an extension of our previous discussion. I read over <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.12548.pdf">RLPrompt: Optimizing Discrete Text Prompts with Reinforcement Learning</a>, a paper our advisor mentioned might be relevant to our Reinforcement Learning approach. In preparation for coding on the cluster, I also went through the process of pulling up a Jupyter Notebook on the UMD Cluster we will be working on. All this stuff is confusing and there is so much to learn, but it will be a good research process for our group to eventually split up code and work in parallel. Hopefully I won’t fall behind, given that I haven’t done any of this sort of coding before, but I hear it’s not too hard to pick up. At the end, we started formulating the “Experiment Plan” i.e. formalizing what datasets/methods/models/visualization tools we plan to use. It turns out finding a good dataset with groups of people and their faces is more difficult than it sounds – we will continue with this tomorrow.</p> </li> </ul> <p>After research, ZS drove SS, SK, AB, and I to Target, where I picked up some snacks (now that I am writing this I realize I forgot to get fruit), including Yogurt and Granola Bars (which will be good post-morning-swim snacks) and some Bagel Bites for when the weekend food situation is dire. I had CFA for dinner with AB and SS, where AB and I debated the pros and cons for answers to “which superpower would you pick to have, and why?” (we both agreed on Teleportation but he had some strong opinions for why some of the other options I had considered weren’t as good). For the rest of the day (I imagine the rest of the week will be similar due to the rain), I mainly stayed inside and worked on my own things.</p> <p>#### <u>Day 18 (June 22nd)</u></p> <p>Week 3, Day 4</p> <ul> <li> <p>8:30 - 9:00 AM: Morning swim. Got there a bit late so went for a shorter workout, but still got in around 30ish laps, which is solid. It’s going to be drizzling every one of these mornings, so I’ll have to get used to that. I do feel like they heat up the pool more when it’s raining because it felt really nice to get in the pool today.</p> </li> <li> <p>10:00 AM - 12:00 PM: Today was the second week of my advisor’s group meetings with her overall research group (including graduate students, other students, etc.). Since we are due to eventually present in one of these meetings (on July 6th), I’ve decided that it’s good to listen in to the other research projects people are interested in to get a general sense of what we will talk about and what is being done. Our presentation is only supposed to be 5-10 minutes, so relatively informal, whereas these group meetings are around 2 hours, but I still think it is worthwhile to listen in. Today, a grad student discussed his Upcoming Projects, including Extreme Multi-label Compression/Online Data Pruning/GNNs for Tensor Completion. I will try to have these notes typed up and available in the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Notes</code> folder sometime within the next week. My group worked more on our research project – getting a face detector and gender classifier to work in preparation for our overall project framework, and I joined in shortly after.</p> </li> <li> <p>1:15 - 4:00 PM: In the afternoon, we continued working on our overall framework. SS has been working on testing out a face detector and gender classifier using pretrained models found in literature (e.g. YOLOv8 for face), as we want to have a pipeline to at least begin testing out our different approaches. I am hoping to work with her more on the coding aspect as I feel like there is a lot for me to learn in that regard, and I think I will need to work more independently/more remotely outside of research hours to do so. During research, AF and I have been focusing on thinking about what datasets we want to use for our training set in our “linear head” approach. The issue is that existing face/general-purpose datasets like LAION-5B are extremely large (tens of TBs) and not feasible given the storage space we have access to. We will need to figure out how to get subsets of this larger dataset and ask our advisor for the feasibility of this approach. As a group, we also tried to formalize our overall framework some more. This is kind of vague, but the goal is to formulate a detailed Experiment Plan with potential issues, ideas, etc. before we end up running any experiments. I’m hoping we’ll have a really solid one done tomorrow so we can share it with our advisor early next week. Also, a personal goal is to code more and familiarize myself with the models we are thinking of using/the general coding process for ML, which I think my group members are much more familiar with.</p> </li> <li> <p>4:00 - 5:00 PM: We had an optional talk hosted jointly with the Biology and Math REUs here at UMD this summer. Professor Najib M. El-Sayed presented his work on “Models in profiling host pathogen interactions.” I thought the talk itself was good, as the speaker was quite engaged and interactive. Since the talk was more optional, the remainder of my REU group elected not to go and pretty much only half the overall REU-CAAR group showed.</p> </li> </ul> <p>For dinner, I grabbed some QD before heading back to the dorms. I played some Catan with XG, SS, and DS, which took up quite a bit of time. The games itself were a bit unlucky for me so I didn’t have as much fun as I could have (I think I also had a bad strategy in picking the starting board position). In the future, I will try to get myself to spend more time working on CodeForces, research, and exercising if it’s not raining out, as those activities seem more productive overall. Last day of the work week coming up tomorrow! I’m going to try to sleep a bit earlier, swim a bit more, and have a solid last work day.</p> <h4 id="day-19-june-23rd-"><u>Day 19 (June 23rd) </u></h4> <p>Week 3, Day 5</p> <ul> <li> <p>8:30 - 9:00 AM: Morning swim. I’m getting consistent with the morning workout, no matter how I feel, so I’m pretty happy with that. I also got there a bit earlier than normal so I got to swim around 25 minutes today. There was a group before me that seemed like swimmers preparing for a meet, so there was a lot of moving and reshuffling of the lane lines (which I felt bad about – since I was the only one in the pool, I kept asking where I should swim to make the lifeguards’ jobs most convenient). Oh well.</p> </li> <li> <p>10:00 - 12:00 PM: We continued with our work from the previous days. SS got the face detector &amp; gender classification model to run, but after testing the gender classification model on the segmented faces, we noticed that the classification results were not that great (for example, for photos with three male and three female doctors, the classifier erroneously predicted – and with high confidence – that one of the male doctors was female and that all three female doctors were male). In light of that, I spent the morning trying to run YOLOv8’s object detector (to recognize the box frame of a person) and then pass that through the gender classifier model to see if the results would differ. We also made a team GitHub page which is really great as it will allow easier workflow and collaboration for projects with similar code (like the person vs. face detector approach).</p> </li> <li> <p>1:15 - 4:00 PM: After continuing with my morning experiments, I didn’t find much improvement in the images I tested. We found that the “person” detector is not that accurate (as for images with people bunched together, the YOLOv8 detector draws a box around parts of multiple people and labels them as one person). The gender classification model wasn’t all that great either, as it still gave me errors. We will need to ask our advisor if there is any powerful, open-source gender classifier we can use for this step or if we need to make and train one ourselves (this shouldn’t be too bad but will take work). Potential goals for this weekend is to streamline the testing/image copying process more (currently, there is no way to view images when ssh’ing into the cluster we use, so we need to manually add and move them to our local computers every time we want to view the results of the face detector). A possible approach is to make a pipeline that allows for more effective code running and testing.</p> </li> </ul> <p>I am feeling a bit more tired than normal after research, so maybe I’ll have to sleep earlier. After research, DS, AB, and I attempted to organize a group to head out for dinner at the College Park Grill, but we were unsuccessful in convinicing others. Regardless, we went out for dinner, which was relatively fun and quite social. I learned a bunch more about them, their research experiences, and about their opinions about the REU. After coming back, I solved a more-annoying-than-difficult CodeForces problem that turned out to be 1700 rated. I definitely want to keep coding, but will need to spend more time on research as well outside of the normal working hours. Onto the weekend!</p> <p>#### <u>Day 20 (June 24th) </u></p> <ul> <li> <p>10:00 AM - 1:00 PM: I spent the morning working on a <a href="https://codeforces.com/contest/1842">CodeForces Contest</a> – I ended up participating with my alternate account. In the future, I think I want to avoid this as I need to get over the fact that rating doesn’t matter all that much. I managed to get the first two (the first one took a bit longer than I would have liked) but got stumped on the third one. After the contest, I worked and talked through the problem with AB. We found the O(n^2) solution and I promptly coded it up – not thinking about the complexity – until I got TLE on test case 3. After some failed attempts to fix the complexity, I stumbled on a better solution posted by a user in Discord, took a while to understand it with AB again, and coded that up. All in all, it was fun to go through the contest and to discuss with AB. I will definitely need more practice to hit my goal of Expert by the end of the year.</p> </li> <li> <p>1:00 PM - 3:00 PM: After the contest, I grabbed some Panda from STAMP (they, along with CFA, are the only ones open in the Union on Saturdays) and then promptly “rewarded myself” (I told myself I deserved it since we are more or less solidifed with our research project idea now) by buying $200 Beats headphones with my Terrapin Express Card. The meal plan covers $1400 over the summer, giving us roughly $140 to spend per week on food. After three weeks, I’m now at around $900 due to this purchase, which puts me slightly ahead of pace. I’ve been spending around $10 per meal so I think the purchase is justifiable – also, I wanted to have a pair of headphones. Definitely have to put this to good use though. :)</p> </li> <li> <p>3:30 - 5:00 PM: Went for a longish swim at the pool. I ended up going for 50+ laps, which took around 40 minutes. The weather report said it was going to thunderstorm all afternoon, but it did not. Since it was quite hot out, the workout was a lot of fun, and it was great to get some good exercise in even over the weekend. My guess is I’ll take the day off tomorrow from swimming.</p> </li> </ul> <p>In the evening, I ate some leftover CFA Veggie Wrap I was able to get for free from research on Friday. I’m hoping to get a bit of work done for research as well, like running some more test experiments or setting up a basic “test set” of groups of people for our models to test.</p> <p>#### <u>Day 21 (June 25th) </u></p> <ul> <li>I went for a morning tennis session with AF. It was really hot out, so I decided to take a quick swim in the pool afterwards, which was quite nice. There was a lot of people at the pool compared to normal, but that’s kind of to be expected. Note to self: get/wear sunscreen next time.</li> </ul> <p>In the afternoon, I spent a bit more time working on some CodeForces problems (1800E1 and 1800E2) – to solve them, I had to look over the solutions to understand/code them afterwards. I then went for a pizza dinner with SS, AF, SK, and DS – as you might notice, these activities are usually with the same subset of people, but I think it would be nice to get more of the REU group involved. All in all, it was a solid, chill weekend. I would like to work on more research in future weekends, but I felt like this weekend was still relatively “productive” work-wise with the CodeForces contest.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="caar"/><category term="research"/><category term="cs"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Week 3 of my Summer 2023 experience @ REU-CAAR.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">REU-CAAR, Week 2</title><link href="https://dyang5.github.io/blog/2023/REUCAAR-week2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="REU-CAAR, Week 2"/><published>2023-06-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://dyang5.github.io/blog/2023/REUCAAR-week2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://dyang5.github.io/blog/2023/REUCAAR-week2/"><![CDATA[<h4 id="day-8-june-12th"><u>Day 8 (June 12th)</u></h4> <p>Literature Review (pt. 5) &amp; Further Discussion</p> <ul> <li>10:00 AM - 12:00 PM: We started off the day by discussing our project ideas further and continuing to read papers. My main goal today (which will continue into tomorrow) has been and will be to type up the notes I’ve taken and to read the most relevant papers more closely. I’m quite happy with the progress I made on this front (the notes I have after today reach almost 8 pages). For email privacy concerns, I will avoid sharing the Overleaf document but will keep a running copy of the work we’ve done in the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Notes</code> section of this repo.</li> <li>12:00 PM - 1:30 PM: This is typically our lunch break period, but today we had a group lunch hosted by the REU (Q-Doba) and listened to a talk by one of the mentors Laxman Dhulipala on his group’s project “Parallel Algorithms for High Dimensional Clustering.” I quite enjoyed the talk – it was really fun to connect concepts I’ve learned in my Algorithms and Compilers classes and from my competitive programming experience.</li> <li>1:30 PM - 4:00 PM: We wrapped up the day by doing much of the same work I did in the morning (again, will need to continue to do this tomorrow). We’re hoping to finalize our talking points with Furong for tomorrow in preparation for an early Wednesday morning meeting. Papers I took notes on today include the Generative Adversarial Networks, Denoising Diffusion Probabilistic Model / Denoising Diffusion Implicit Model, Debiasing Methods Survey, and the Fair Diffusion paper. Tomorrow, I’ll continue with the Adversarial Classifier, Debiasing Vision-Language Models via Biased Prompts, CLIP, and finish up the Debiasing Methods Survey papers for note-taking.</li> </ul> <p>After research, I ended up checking out the Union’s Campus Store (I’ll definitely get something before the program ends) before eating at CFA with PM, MA, NL, DS, and ZS. I did some Codeforces before playing some board games with SS, AZ, AB, ML, and DS to round out the night. I went swimming this morning before research, and I felt that it was nice to wake up earlier and get some exercise in. In the future, I’ll continue to do this as I can.</p> <h4 id="day-9-june-13th"><u>Day 9 (June 13th)</u></h4> <p>Literature Review (pt. 6) &amp; Meeting Prep</p> <ul> <li>10:00 AM - 12:00 PM: After another morning swim (note: I’m happy I’m getting exercise in before research) and a quick breakfast from the IRB cafe (the second in as many days), the research day continued on like it has the last few days: more paper reading and LaTeXing my notes on the attached Notes document. At 11:00 PM, I Zoomed into to a PhD defense on “On Algorithms, Fairness, and Incentives” as it seemed relevant to some of the work we’re doing in the REU and because I wanted to see what a PhD defense session is like (a few years down the line, I might be in the same position). While I wasn’t able to follow as closely, I still think it was a worthwhile experience.</li> <li>1:15 - 4:00 PM: Since SS was working remotely today, we decided to spend the morning session a bit more focused on individual reading/note-taking. In the afternoon session, we were more focused on prepping our talking points for a meeting with our advisor tomorrow. At around 3:00 PM, we zoomed in with SS to discuss as a group before jotting down our main points for tomorrow. Hopefully the meeting goes well – it would be sad to hear that the ideas we’ve been reading and thinking about for the last week and a half are not fruitful and/or attainable. That being said, I am sure the meeting will give us new direction into our project, which is an exciting avenue given that we’ve mostly been reading papers thus far.</li> </ul> <p>After research today, I rode in XG’s car as he went to get some gas, before driving to STAMP (Student Union) for some early dinner. Our research group had decided yesterday that we wanted to watch the new Spiderman Movie (Spider-Man: Across the Spider-Verse) and so we went to the theatre at 6 today to do so. After managing to convince another car owner at the REU and a few other REU participants, a large group of us (XG, AF, SS, me, PM, MA, JS, SK, DS, and NL) convened at the theatre and had a great time watching the movie. There was a bit of a debacle with the seats – it turns out that when my research group ordered the tickets yesterday, we had actually ordered for 6 PM that day. When movie watchers came in and said we were in their seats, we were in a bit of a pickle. After a bit of shuffling at the start of the movie (and some manager assistance), we were relegated to the back of the theatre, which was a perfectly fine seating arrangement as we at least got to watch the movie. We came back and a subset of us played some Codenames. Definitely a fun experience and a crazy day.</p> <h4 id="day-10-june-14th"><u>Day 10 (June 14th)</u></h4> <p>Meeting Day</p> <ul> <li>9:00 - 10:00 AM: Our first official group meeting with our advisor! Since our advisor is in China this summer, she will only be able to Zoom in either early in the morning or late at night. So far, the plan is to meet just once a week for an hour, so we will need to make really good use of this meeting time. We met on the first day a bit more informally – to talk expectations and discuss projects – but today was different. Our advisor FH was joined by two grad students. As a group, we had prepared a meeting abstract and points to talk about (as well as my Overleaf Note document which I unfortunately don’t think anyone else took the time to look over), and so we began by discussing project ideas and the approaches we read in our lit review.</li> </ul> <blockquote> <p>Our topic relates to Fairness in Vision-Language Models. Specifically, we want to look into “contextualized bias” in text prompts for diffusion models. For example, “give me a photo of a doctor” may have the <em>implicit gender bias</em> (that relates doctors to males), whereas “give me a photo of a hospital” has a contextualized bias in the sense that hospitals have doctors, who will likely be generated as predominately male. We discussed three types of approaches (pre-processing, in-processing, and post-processing) and their feasability. A pre-processing approach may be to augment the dataset. During training of a diffusion model, there may be a gender imbalance in the images of the dataset (more males than females for a given occupation). We would like to see if we can make the dataset more balanced to support a more fair model – we may be able to work on this with the help of domain translators (potentially even a diffusion model). The in-processing approach we discussed involves focusing on fine-tuning one or two layers in a VLM. This type of approach was the least clear among the three for me, and may be difficult to actually implement. Finally, for post-processing approaches, we talked about potentially fine-tuning the text encoder for CLIP (since there is bias on the “text side” of these VLMs). We also discussed potential embedding searches to solve the issue of contextualized bias.</p> </blockquote> <ul> <li> <p>Forgive me if these notes are unclear – as always, this is simply my understanding of what we discussed and may be wrong. All in all, the meeting went fine. Our advisor stressed the importance of nailing down a topic that has both a reasonable approach and that is novel/meaningful. She mentioned that we are still okay pace-wise (given that we have narrowed our topic area down), but that we should continue to think of <strong>novel approaches</strong> rather than simply extending previous work. This will be a tough task but I’m sure my group will manage. Furthermore, our advisor is more hands-off than my previous research advisors. This is not a bad thing, but my group and I will need to be independent and to take advantage of our available resources; a goal of ours will be to more consistently reach out and discuss ideas/brainstorm as I’ve been doing on this blog. We made the plan to try and update our advisor and the graduate students twice a week; adding a grad student as another project mentor is also a big goal of ours as it may help give us more direction. We’ll definitely see how these ideas pan out, but I’m still hopeful that our research this summer (especially the next few days, where we will need to continue to discuss ideas/read papers) will be fruitful.</p> </li> <li> <p>10:00 AM - 12:00 PM, 1:30 PM - 4:00 PM: I’m combining these sections as the main focus of the day was the meeting. After the meeting, we discussed next steps together as a group. We are hoping to make our goals actionable and concrete to prepare ourselves for the coming stretch.</p> <ul> <li>Throughout the afternoon, we copied over our meeting notes (which we typed during the meeting) into a more legible/readable format, and to better sort the ideas we discussed with our advisor. Tomorrow, I think we will take more actionable steps and explore and discuss different approaches, analyzing their novelty and their feasability. From what it sounds like, we are still on pace with our advisor’s expectations (we narrowed down our subect area relatively well, but now we want to be specific about the work we want to do and to make it clear why it’s important/novel), which is always a good sign. We’ll definitely keep at it.</li> </ul> </li> </ul> <p>After research today, a large group of the REU program went to play tennis (PM, MA, XG, NL, SK, SS, DS, and I). We were only able to borrow five rackets, but we rotated. Some of them were beginners and so we taught them the basic techniques and everyone seemed to pick it up quickly/enjoy it. For dinner, we ended up noticing that a dining hall near the gym was crowded with people. Since there is a National History Day (NHD) competition of sorts happening until Friday, the dining halls are open more. A quick show of our ID card got us into the big dining hall for free (I think the workers may have mistaken us with NHD students), so I certainly can’t complain about that. It was good getting out with a big group of people and exercising by playing tennis (I missed my morning swim due to the early meeting with my advisor), and especially taking a well-deserved break after research today. All in all, a long and tiring day, but one that I’ll hopefully look back on in a week or two and remember fondly.</p> <h4 id="day-11-june-15th"><u>Day 11 (June 15th)</u></h4> <p>Project Brainstorm, Extended (Day 1)</p> <ul> <li> <p>8:30 AM - 9:00 AM: Morning Swim. This is an activity I want to stay consistent with as I feel like to force myself to sleep earlier, to wake up earlier in the morning, and to get some exercise in before research. Physical health is important!</p> </li> <li> <p>10:00 AM - 12:00 PM: Our goal today (this will probably be our goal for the next few days as well) was to continue to work on fine-tuning our project ideas and finding a novel approach to fairness in diffusion models. My advisor’s research group (consisting of grad students, interns, and the REU students this summer) host Thursday morning (10 - 12) group meetings to discuss research progress being made, and my group decided to join to listen in. In the future, I think this will be valuable to hear about what everyone is working on and to learn from others’ research progress; it turns out we are also scheduled to present sometime later in the summer. Today, a grad student talked about “Bilevel Optimization Problems in Machine Learning and Efficient Solvers” – I will try to keep notes on each of the meetings as a TeX file in the notes folder.</p> </li> <li> <p>1:30 PM - 4:00 PM: It’s great to read the work done and to think about ideas, and I prefer to note-take during the process (which helps me understand the papers better), but at a certain point, paper reading will only got you so far. As a group, we thought it might be a good idea to set up our code environments to prepare to implement/test some of the approaches we’ve been reading about. I haven’t done any previous work with PyTorch or Virtual Environments, so AF helped me set both of these up. SS and I then worked together on a <a href="https://pytorch.org/tutorials/beginner/basics/quickstart_tutorial.html">PyTorch Tutorial</a> to close out the day. To address one of our other goals (which is more consistent updates/outlining our group’s goals each day), SS had the idea of creating a Trello Board to organize work flow. This is my first time using Trello but I think it will be good to outline what we are working on each day and update our mentors with progress using the Trello Board.</p> </li> <li> <p>4:00 - 5:00 PM: My REU group (REU-CAAR) joined up with students from the other REU Programs (I believe REU-MATH and REU-BRIDGE) at UMD this summer to hear from Erin Molloy on a Computational Biology talk: “Models and methods for reconstructing population-level evolutionary histories and relationships to tumor phylogenetics.”</p> </li> </ul> <p>After research, I ended up checking out the campus bookstore in the Student Union (my third time going and not buying anything) and then grabbed dinner from QD. I then ended up coming back to do some Codeforces before heading out to play some soccer/football with DS, PM, MA, and NL. On another note, I learned today that we don’t have free access to the dining hall – we’ll have to pay the $14 for lunch or $18 for dinner, which in my opinion is a complete rip-off. I think I’ll stick to STAMP for lunch and dinner (each of the meals are around 10-12 dollars, which is well under the allocated “$14 per lunch and dinner if no breakfast” meal plan that we were given at the start of the program). In terms of physical activity, I think I’m doing good with exercising (including swimming in the morning) and socializing with others. I’m hoping that the research progress will follow soon once we solidify our approach!</p> <h4 id="day-12-june-16th"><u>Day 12 (June 16th)</u></h4> <p>Project Brainstorm, Extended (Day 2)</p> <ul> <li> <p>8:30 - 9:00 AM: Got in a good morning swim again. I went for around 25 minutes and got in a good workout.</p> </li> <li> <p>10:00 AM - 12:00 PM: After trying to set up our accounts for cluster access and applying yesterday, we checked earlier today to see if our accounts had been approved. My login details weren’t working and neither were my group’s, so we sent a few messages back and forth with our PI and the UMIACS Help Desk to get everything sorted out. We now have cluster access (I don’t think I’ll be using it until after we’ve solidified our project ideas, but the rest of the group seemed really excited). I read a few new papers, including <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2110.02711.pdf">DiffusionCLIP: Text-Guided Diffusion Models for Robust Image Manipulation</a> and <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2105.12931.pdf">YOLO5Face</a>, a face detection model that we may end up using.</p> </li> <li> <p>1:30 - 4:00 PM: I spent most of the afternoon finishing up the papers I had started reading in the morning and briefly starting setting up a Virtual Environment, PyTorch, etc. on my cluster account. When I’m not sure what progress I can make, I tend to default to reading papers and trying to glean the relevant ideas/processes, and so I’ve been doing a lot of that lately. Progress is definitely going to be incremental, but we’ll keep at it.</p> </li> </ul> <p>After research, I went to a nearby barber shop to get a haircut, and then headed back to the dorms before heading back out to play tennis with AB. The weather report said there might’ve been a thunderstorm, but just like in the morning (when it said it was going to thunder around the time I was going to swim), it was completely off. I then went to a nearby Poke place with ZS and SS for dinner, since the Student Union unfortunately closes early on Fridays. My group also had a 9:30 PM meeting with Bill Gasarch to talk about our project and how everything is going. I feel like this was helpful, but it was also just great to talk to Bill given how enthusiastic and energetic he is. I’d say he’s definitely a big reason why REU-CAAR seems to be successful. After the meeting, I talked with SS and AF (XG is a UMD student so he Zoomed in from home) about project expectations and concerns/how to address them. Afterwards, I solved a harder (~1600 rating) Codeforces problem with AF, which was pretty fun as well. Lots of cool people in this REU – I definitely want to keep learning and working throughout.</p> <h4 id="day-13-june-17th"><u>Day 13 (June 17th)</u></h4> <p>Weekend Day! Woke up around 10:30 AM, went for lunch at Panda Express in STAMP (a pleasant surprise – they’re the only restaurant open on Saturdays) before heading for a post-lunch swim. I then gathered with DS, SS, AF, LH, SK to grab some Pho for dinner before playing some Hanabi with DS, SS, and SK afterwards. Tomorrow I’m headed to DC with the REU group and then to hopefully meet with some of my high school friends.</p> <h4 id="day-14-june-18th"><u>Day 14 (June 18th)</u></h4> <p>Second day of the three day weekend. A subset of our REU group (including AG – our grad mentor – AZ, ML, DS, AB, SS, JS, SK, NL, LH, and ZS) went to DC for the day. We went to the Museum of Natural History, which was alright (I’ve been there a few times before but I really liked the Gems exhibit). We then walked over to a Sandwich spot for lunch – thank god it’s getting subsidized because I don’t think I would have gotten it otherwise. We then went to the Washington Monument before a group of us (me, SS, ML, LH, NL) branched off to go to ShareTea rather than another museum. It turns out my plans with my high school friends fell through. The overall trip time was from 10 - 6 (including train and walking times), which is quite a lot and perhaps not worth it. All in all, though, it was good to get out with a larger REU group.</p> <p>After coming back, I made sure to hit the pool for some exercise (even though I walked nearly 26,000 steps and like 12 miles today) with SS, and we got some Acai Bowls for dinner.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="caar"/><category term="research"/><category term="cs"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Week 2 of my Summer 2023 experience @ REU-CAAR.]]></summary></entry></feed>